Jean-Guillaume's first deal.
Sa première OP, Jean-Guillaume.
Let's go!
Let's go !
Applause
Applaudissements
Thank you.
Merci.
My favorites!
Mes préférés !
How's it going?
Ça va ?
Alright.
Ok.
Everything going well so far?
Tout se passe bien jusqu'à présent ?
Shall we get a bit more into the heart of the matter?
On rentre un peu plus dans le vif du sujet ?
Alright.
Ok.
Let's go!
Let's go !
So,
Alors,
Maud, how much time do we have again?
Maud, on a combien de temps déjà ?
We've got five sections to cover, so let's keep it moving.
On a cinq parties à voir, donc on va débiter.
We'll start with the negotiation process,
On va commencer par le processus
then we'll look at the ten qualities
de négociation, ensuite on va voir les dix qualités
of a good negotiator, a few tips
du bon négociateur, quelques tips
I've got for you to get started,
que j'ai pour vous pour démarrer
and especially to keep in mind.
et à garder en tête surtout.
Negotiating your commission split,
Négocier son split de rémunération,
how you can negotiate, what
comment on peut négocier, quels sont
the triggers are for that, and how to negotiate
les triggers là-dessus, et comment négocier
with an investor.
un investisseur ?
Does that agenda work for you?
Ça vous convient comme agenda ?
Cool.
Cool.
This is going to be intense.
Ça va être indense.
Take notes as we go.
On prend des notes.
If it feels too fast, just click pause.
Si vous voyez que ça passe trop vite, petit clic.
If not, we'll see if we can send you the slides.
On verra si on peut vous envoyer les slides sinon.
Alright?
Ok ?
Introduction.
Introduction.
So, wow!
Alors, waouh !
I have to start with the basics.
Je suis obligé de commencer par la base.
You might not like it,
Elle ne va pas vous plaire,
or maybe you will,
ou elle va vous plaire,
but I want us all on the same page.
mais j'aimerais qu'on se mette d'accord.
Who here today
Qui aujourd'hui
feels like
se sent
a salesperson?
un vendeur ?
Yeah, raise your hand, don't be shy.
Ouais, levez la main, n'hésitez pas.
Okay.
Ok.
Who here today doesn't feel at all
Qui aujourd'hui ne se sent pas du tout
like a salesperson?
un vendeur ?
Alright.
Ok.
So, just to be totally clear,
Alors, déjà, juste qu'on se mette bien d'accord,
we're all salespeople.
on est tous des vendeurs.
Now, I know some of you,
Alors, je sais que certains d'entre vous,
you don't like the word 'salesperson',
vous n'aimez pas le terme vendeur,
because it sounds kind of negative
parce que ça a une connotation négative
like a rug salesman,
de vendeur de tapis,
or a whatever salesman,
vendeur de whatever,
whatever you've heard.
de ce que vous avez entendu.
But actually,
Mais en fait,
the truth is, if you really think about it,
la vérité, si on analyse bien,
why do we talk about negotiation?
pourquoi on parle de négociation ?
Because every day,
Parce que tous les jours,
you're negotiating.
vous négociez.
Who here has a job?
Qui est salarié ?
Okay?
Ok ?
When you negotiate a raise,
Quand vous négociez votre salaire à la hausse,
what do you think that is?
vous croyez que c'est quoi ?
Aren't you making a sale there?
Vous ne faites pas une vente là ?
You're making a sale.
Vous faites une vente.
When you negotiate with your wife
Quand vous négociez avec votre femme
or your kids to go out,
ou vos enfants pour sortir,
to come to Marchand de Bien,
venir à Marchand de Bien,
on Monday or Tuesday,
le lundi, mardi,
like that,
comme ça,
you had to negotiate.
vous avez dû négocier.
You had to negotiate, explain.
Vous avez dû négocier, expliquer.
When you justify a price,
Quand vous justifiez un prix,
or a decision,
une décision,
when you get home,
quand vous allez rentrer chez vous,
you're going to say,
vous allez dire,
hey, listen,
dis-moi,
we're going to move.
on va déménager.
It didn't work out like that.
Ça n'a pas marché comme ça.
We're going to need to prepare a bit more.
Il va falloir se préparer un peu plus.
Honestly, I wouldn't recommend doing it that way.
Je vous déconseille de le faire comme ça, d'ailleurs.
It would be more like,
Ce serait plutôt,
listen babe,
écoute bébé,
you told me,
tu m'as parlé,
you wanted us to make twice,
tu voulais qu'on gagne deux fois,
or three times as much.
trois fois plus.
So I checked,
J'ai regardé,
and it turns out that in the city,
et il se trouve que dans la ville,
over there,
là-bas,
I already found some others.
j'ai trouvé déjà des autres.
And it's a whole different vibe.
Et ce n'est pas le même délire.
You come in with data,
Vous venez avec la data,
with information,
l'information,
and you're basically selling,
et vous êtes en train de faire de la vente,
actually,
en fait,
all the time.
tout le temps.
So negotiation,
Donc la négociation,
is about getting what you want,
c'est obtenir ce que vous voulez,
or at least,
ou en tout cas,
trying to put yourself
essayer de vous mettre
in the best possible position
dans la meilleure position
to get what you want.
pour obtenir ce que vous voulez.
And me,
Et moi,
I'm not afraid to say it,
je n'ai pas peur de le dire,
I'm actually proud
je suis même fier
to say it,
de le dire,
we're all salespeople,
on est des vendeurs,
every one of us.
tous.
And those who see that
Et ceux qui voient ça
as something negative,
comme quelque chose de négatif,
at some point,
à un moment donné,
explain to me
expliquez-moi
what exactly is
qu'est-ce que c'est
selling
la vente
or negotiating.
ou la négociation.
Because to me,
Parce que pour moi,
it's basically
c'est du coup
just selling.
de la vente.
Getting your idea across,
Faire passer une idée,
influencing.
influencer.
When you want to raise money,
Quand vous voulez lever de l'argent,
you're making a sale.
faites une vente.
When you want to sell a project,
Quand vous voulez vendre un projet,
When tomorrow,
Quand demain,
you're an expert in renovations
vous êtes expert en travaux
and you have to justify yourself,
et vous devez justifier,
you're selling
vous faites de la vente
all the time,
tout le temps,
non-stop,
non-stop,
it never ends.
ça ne s'arrête pas.
All the time.
Tout le temps.
So negotiating,
Donc négocier,
what is it?
c'est quoi ?
It's basically
C'est effectivement
closing a deal,
closer un deal,
selling your plan.
vendre son plan.
When you need to negotiate
Quand vous devez négocier
with a partner
avec un associé
to get them to join you
pour qu'il vous rejoigne
and work with you,
à travailler avec vous,
you have to show them the vision.
vous devez lui mettre la vision.
What do you call that?
Ça s'appelle quoi ?
You're making a sale
Vous lui faites une vente
to get them on board.
pour vous rejoindre.
So,
Donc,
convincing someone else.
convaincre une autre personne.
The goal,
L'objectif,
of course,
bien sûr,
is to align everyone's interests.
c'est d'aligner les intérêts.
Alright?
D'accord ?
We're not here to sell just anything,
On n'est pas pour vendre
to just anyone,
n'importe quoi
or everything to anyone.
et tout à n'importe qui.
No.
Non.
You're selling the vision.
Vous vendez la vision.
Me,
Moi,
today,
aujourd'hui,
my goal,
mon but,
right now,
c'est de vous vendre,
this morning,
ce matin,
it was to sell you
c'était de vous vendre
my vision of the right mindset,
la vision que j'ai du mindset
so you stay grounded
pour que vous soyez ancré
for at least five years.
pendant cinq ans minimum.
Otherwise,
Sinon,
you won't get
vous n'allez pas avoir
the success you deserve.
le succès que vous méritez.
And now,
Et là,
my vision,
ma vision,
is to sell you
c'est de vous vendre
on negotiation.
la négociation.
So,
Donc,
why is this key?
pourquoi c'est clé ?
Because it impacts
Parce que ça impacte
directly your income.
directement vos revenus.
Who wants to make more money?
Qui veut gagner plus ?
Okay.
Ok.
Thanks.
Merci.
100%.
100%.
I know you’re a bit sluggish.
Je sais que vous êtes un peu mou.
I’m going to wake you up.
Je vais vous réveiller.
So,
Donc,
what I mean by that,
ce que je veux dire par là,
is that
c'est que
each of you
chacun d'entre vous
wants to increase your income.
veut augmenter ses revenus.
For that,
Pour ça,
you need to justify,
il faut justifier,
create value.
créer de la valeur.
That’s going to have an impact
Ça va avoir un impact
on your personal life.
sur votre vie personnelle.
If tomorrow,
Si demain,
you make bad deals
vous prenez les mauvaises négociations
or bad decisions
ou les mauvaises décisions
because you weren’t able,
parce que vous n'avez pas été capable,
who’s ever found themselves
qui s'est déjà retrouvé
super frustrated
méga frustré
about losing an argument
d'avoir perdu un argument
with someone
avec quelqu'un
once in your life
une fois dans sa life
and you weren't
et vous n'avez pas été
in the place where...
à l'endroit où...
It's because
C'est à cause du fait
you weren't
que vous n'avez pas été
a good salesperson.
bon vendeur.
You didn't sell
Vous n'avez pas bien vendu
the opportunity well.
l'opportunité.
You didn't sell it well...
Vous n'avez pas bien vendu...
So,
Alors,
there might be other factors,
il peut y avoir d'autres facteurs,
but you also need
mais il faut aussi
to question yourself about that
se remettre en question là-dessus
and that's the main difference
et c'est la différence majeure
between top performers
entre les top performers
and everyone else.
et les autres.
So,
Donc,
if you want to be average,
si vous voulez être moyen,
average,
average,
leave the room
quittez la salle
and go check out
et allez voir
other competitors.
d'autres concurrents.
And I'm not here
Et je ne suis pas là
to badmouth the others,
pour cracher sur les autres,
quite the opposite,
au contraire,
but we're not here
mais on n'est pas là
to be average in our group.
pour être moyen chez nous
We want to give you
et on veut vous délivrer
every year,
chaque année
the very best of ourselves.
le meilleur de nous-mêmes.
So,
Donc,
to be a top performer,
pour être top performer,
you have to be a beast
il faut être un monstre
at negotiation.
en négociation.
That means reading books
Ça passe par lire des livres
about negotiation,
sur la négociation,
doing role plays,
vous faire des role play,
making deals,
ça passe par faire des deals,
being creative,
être créatif,
doing case studies,
faire des case studies,
and so on.
etc.
So,
Donc,
that's why we're here.
c'est pour ça qu'on est là.
OK.
OK.
So,
Donc,
the negotiation process.
le processus de négociation.
Alright,
Alors,
let's keep going.
on va enchaîner.
Take some photos.
Prenez des photos.
The first one,
La première,
So, there are seven steps.
donc c'est sept étapes.
The first step,
La première étape,
is preparation.
c'est la préparation.
That's 80% of the deal.
C'est 80% du deal.
Why?
Pourquoi ?
You need to know
Vous devez connaître
your ideal goal,
votre objectif idéal,
and your minimum goal.
votre objectif minimum.
The BATNA,
Le BATNA,
that's your best alternative option.
c'est votre best alternative option.
So,
Donc,
meaning,
c'est-à-dire,
what's your best option
quelle est votre meilleure option
if you don't get
si jamais vous n'obtenez pas
what you want?
ce que vous voulez ?
What's your plan B?
Quel est votre plan B ?
If you have one.
S'il y en a un.
Sometimes,
Des fois,
you'll only have plan A.
ce ne sera que votre plan A.
Otherwise,
Sinon,
it'll really be plan B.
ce sera effectivement le plan B.
And leverage.
Et le leverage.
Leverage,
Le leverage,
could be using time,
ça peut être utiliser le temps,
money, or urgency.
l'argent ou l'urgence.
So,
Donc,
you need to know
il faut savoir
before a negotiation,
avant une négociation,
first,
déjà,
what levers
quels sont les leviers
you'll be able to use
que vous allez pouvoir utiliser
to negotiate well.
pour bien la négocier.
So,
Donc,
if you don't prepare,
sans préparation,
already,
déjà,
you're already losing.
vous êtes en train de perdre.
That's why
C'est pour ça
you have to be prepared
qu'il faut être préparé
before negotiations
avant les négociations
to do whatever it takes.
à tout faire.
Second,
Deuxième,
make an opening,
faire une ouverture,
set the stage.
créer le cadre.
The first five minutes
Les cinq premières minutes
are crucial.
sont clés.
Who's setting the pace?
Qui contrôle le tempo ?
Who's asking the questions?
Qui pose les questions ?
Establish your authority
Installez votre autorité
without being aggressive.
sans agresser.
I was actually downstairs
J'étais justement en bas
earlier
tout à l'heure
with our colleagues
avec nos collègues
who are a bit further along.
un peu plus avancés.
I don't think
Je ne pense pas
they're all
qu'ils sont tous
super,
super,
mega,
méga,
okay?
ok ?
No,
Non,
not all of them.
pas tous.
Some of them,
Il y en a,
they've done one deal,
ils ont fait une OP,
okay,
ok,
two,
deux,
three.
trois.
My point,
Mon point,
what is it?
c'est quoi ?
is that
c'est que
I talked to them
je leur ai parlé
about the ten different
des dix profils
types
différents
of negotiators
des négociateurs
and I told them
et je leur ai dit
that today,
qu'aujourd'hui,
The one who controls
celui qui contrôle
the pace,
le tempo,
is the one
c'est celui
asking the questions,
qui pose les questions,
the one who's running
celui qui gère
the negotiation.
la négociation.
If you walk in,
Si vous rentrez,
and you're just there like,
vous êtes là en mode,
you don't know
vous ne savez pas
how things are going to go,
comment ça va se passer
and then it's the other
et puis c'est l'autre
person asking
personne qui pose
all the questions,
les questions,
you're already
vous êtes déjà
starting to lose.
en train de perdre.
So right away,
Donc déjà,
that dynamic,
cette dynamique,
in the first
dans les premières
five minutes,
cinq minutes,
it's up to you to set it
c'est à vous de la mettre
so you can win
pour pouvoir gagner
their trust
la confiance
and ultimately
et gagner finalement
take control of the deal.
la maîtrise du deal.
That's super important.
C'est très important.
We'll talk about that again in a bit.
On va en reparler après.
Discovery,
La découverte,
so understanding
donc comprendre
their real motivations,
les motivations réelles,
spotting hidden constraints,
identifier les contraintes cachées,
and also picking up on the emotions.
comprendre aussi l'émotion.
So,
Ah ben,
I was talking with your husband,
je parlais avec votre mari,
he wants to sell,
il veut vendre
and then,
et puis,
well,
enfin,
you talk to the husband,
vous parlez au mari,
you've seen the wife,
vous avez vu la femme,
for example,
par exemple,
in a negotiation,
dans une négociation,
a lot of things are going on,
il se passe plein de choses,
and then in the end,
et puis finalement,
your wife,
votre femme,
she told me
elle m'a dit
she didn't want to sell.
qu'elle ne voulait pas vendre.
Are you sure,
Vous êtes sûre,
she wanted to sell?
elle voulait vendre ?
Did she tell you that?
Elle vous a dit ça ?
Maybe her intentions,
Peut-être que ses intentions,
weren't actually to sell.
ce n'étaient pas de vendre.
Maybe the guy
Peut-être que le mec,
just wants to get some info,
il veut prendre juste des informations,
and you wasted your time.
vous avez perdu du temps.
Or maybe it's the other way around.
Ou peut-être que c'est l'inverse.
They're about to have a fight.
Ils vont avoir un fight.
But you want to know that
Mais vous avez envie de le savoir
for your negotiation.
pour votre négociation.
So,
Donc,
most people
la plupart des gens
won't tell you the truth
ne vous diront pas la vérité
right away.
dès le début.
Who are you?
Qui vous êtes ?
Ask people questions
Proposez des questions aux gens
right from the start.
dès le début.
Why are you selling?
Pourquoi vous vendez ?
So,
Donc,
you have to be subtle.
il faut être subtil.
Subtlety,
La subtilité,
is about building trust fast.
c'est de créer la confiance rapidement.
Be a good negotiator.
Être un bon négociateur.
Your number one strength,
Force numéro un,
is trying to capture
c'est d'essayer de capter
people's trust
la confiance des gens
as quickly as possible.
le plus rapidement possible.
People need to understand
Les gens doivent comprendre
that you're genuine.
que vous êtes génuines.
You are,
vous êtes,
I don't know how to say it
je ne sais pas comment dire
in French.
en français ça.
Thanks.
Merci.
Authentic.
Authentique.
Perfect.
Parfait.
You have to be authentic.
Vous devez être authentique.
Don't try
Ne essayez pas
to be someone else.
d'être quelqu'un d'autre.
But,
Par contre,
you can come
vous pouvez venir
with questions
avec des questions
and try
et essayer
but why are you selling them?
mais pourquoi vous les vendre ?
And if it doesn't make sense,
Et si ce n'est pas logique,
dig deeper.
creusez.
But you're in the right place.
Mais vous êtes bien là.
Everyone's here.
Il y a tout le monde.
Why are you selling them?
Pourquoi vous les vendre ?
And actually,
Et en fait,
there are other real motivations
il y a d'autres motivations réelles
that will come up,
qui vont appartenir,
that will show up,
qui vont arriver
and that's what will make
et c'est ce qui va faire
the difference
la différence
between you and everyone else.
entre vous et les autres.
Because when you take an interest
Parce que quand vous vous intéressez
in someone,
à quelqu'un,
when you let people talk,
quand vous laissez parler les gens,
people start
les gens commencent
to feel a connection with you.
à avoir de la sympathie pour vous.
People start to open up.
Les gens commencent à s'ouvrir.
You start building
Vous commencez à créer
a relationship with them.
une relation avec eux.
And you know,
Et bien,
that might be
c'est peut-être
what makes the difference
ce qui va faire la différence
when there are
quand il va y avoir
other people
les autres personnes
who want to knock on the door
qui vont vouloir taper à la porte
and who say,
et qui vont dire
no, but me,
non mais moi,
I really like that guy.
je l'aime bien celui-là.
He's the one
C'est avec lui
I want to work with.
que je veux bosser.
And on top of that,
Si en plus de ça,
if you make the best deals,
vous faites les meilleurs deals,
they'll want
ils vont vouloir
to call you every time.
vous appeler vous chaque fois.
Who's with me?
Qui me suit ?
Alright.
Ok.
Let's keep going.
On enchaîne.
So the one asking
Donc celui qui pose
the questions
les questions
versus negotiating,
contre la négociation,
positioning,
positionnement,
creating value.
créer de la valeur.
You sell before you negotiate.
Vous vendez avant de négocier.
So you can highlight
Donc vous pouvez mettre en avant
speed,
effectivement la rapidité,
security,
la sécurité,
and how simple your offer is.
la simplicité de votre offre.
So your offer,
Donc votre offre,
it needs to be seen
elle doit être perçue
as different.
comme différente.
What could
Qu'est-ce qui peut venir
create value
créer de la valeur
that others can't bring?
que les autres ne vont pas arriver ?
Sometimes,
Des fois,
it's not just about price.
ce n'est pas qu'une question de prix.
you're negotiating a deal
vous négociez un deal
and actually,
et en fait,
it's with elderly people
c'est des personnes âgées
who have lived
qui ont vécu
their whole lives
toute leur vie
in their house
dans leur baraque
and honestly,
et en fait,
it might sound silly,
ça paraît bête,
but they don't want
mais ils ne veulent pas
to sell to a developer
vendre à un promoteur
who's just going to tear everything down
qui va tout défoncer
and build
et qui va construire
something totally different.
un truc complètement différent.
Maybe there's
Peut-être qu'il y a
a fountain
une fontaine
they wanted to keep.
qu'ils auraient aimé garder.
You can say,
Vous pouvez dire,
what about the fountain,
mais c'est quoi la fontaine,
I'll put it
je vais la mettre
right in the middle of the project.
au milieu du projet.
I'll even have your name engraved on it.
Je vais gravé votre nom, même.
That's all part
mais ça fait partie
of being authentic.
de l'authenticité.
Personally, I think that's cool.
Moi, je trouve que c'est cool.
It's cool.
C'est cool.
But if it ends up
Après, si ça vient
ruining the project,
dénaturer le projet,
then I won't suggest it.
je ne vais pas lui proposer.
I'm giving examples.
Je donne des exemples.
We're not here
On n'est pas là
to play tricks
pour faire des feintes
or anything like that.
ou des trucs comme ça.
We're here to actually
On est là pour justement
try to create
essayer de créer
something different.
quelque chose de différent.
Sometimes,
Des fois,
you can be more eco-friendly.
vous pouvez être plus écologique.
Maybe the person
Peut-être que la personne
will tell you,
va vous dire,
you know, they're someone
moi, vous savez que c'est quelqu'un
who works in ecology.
qui travaille dans l'écologie.
You're buying their house.
Vous lui rachetez sa maison.
You can tell them,
Vous allez lui dire,
hey, my project
mais moi, mon projet
is all about solar panels,
est tout en panneau solaire,
and all that.
machin.
And you're actually going to do it.
Et vous allez le faire.
Of course, you're going to do it.
Bien sûr, vous allez le faire.
But my point is,
Mais mon point,
try to find
c'est d'essayer de trouver
what makes you stand out,
le point différenciant
to create value
pour créer de la valeur
that will make you
qui va faire que vous allez
negotiate the deal.
négocier le deal.
Fifth,
Cinquième,
anchoring.
l'ancrage.
The first number
Le premier chiffre
sets the tone for everything.
influence tout.
You shape how the deal is seen.
Fixez la perception du deal.
Whoever anchors
Celui qui ancre
usually wins.
gagne souvent.
If you mention price,
Si vous parlez prix,
you,
vous,
first,
en premier,
you've already lost.
vous avez perdu.
Tell yourself,
Dites-vous,
let's say, for example,
là, par exemple,
we're selling a house
on vend une maison
and the person,
et la personne,
so here,
donc là,
we're selling a house,
on vend une maison,
they ask me,
elle me dit,
what's the best price
c'est quoi le meilleur prix
I should get?
qu'il faut avoir ?
You didn't get it,
Vous n'avez pas compris,
sir.
monsieur.
The offer,
L'offre,
the house,
la maison,
it's at 48 million in offers.
elle est à 48 millions d'offres.
If you want to make us an offer,
Si vous voulez nous faire une offre,
just go ahead and make us an offer.
vous nous faites une offre.
Even if I have a price
Même si j'ai un prix
for the minimum amount,
de combien est le minimum,
I'm not going to tell them.
je ne vais pas lui donner.
If I'm going to sell
Si je vais vendre
at 48.9 million dirhams,
à 48,9 millions de dirhams,
whatever,
peu importe,
let's go,
allez,
I'll draw a diagram,
je vais faire un schéma,
10 million dollars.
10 millions de dollars.
I know that at 9 million dollars,
Je sais qu'à 9 millions de dollars,
I'll sell.
je vends.
But I never tell them that.
Jamais je lui dis.
I say,
Je lui dis,
it's at 10,
c'est à 10,
come with your best offer,
viens avec ta meilleure offre,
so that I can
de manière à ce que je puisse
present it
la proposer
to my partners.
à mes associés.
very often,
très souvent,
it's still me
c'est quand même moi
who of course makes
qui prends bien sûr
the decisions together with everyone,
les décisions en consensus,
but I know
mais je connais
where things stand.
où est-ce qu'on en est.
On the other hand,
Par contre,
I use my partners
j'utilise mes associés
and it's true,
et c'est vrai,
on the edge,
en bord,
by saying,
en disant,
we're the ones who have to
c'est nous qui devons
make the decision
prendre la décision
together.
conjointement.
So,
Donc,
what are the terms,
c'est quoi les termes,
what are the conditions,
c'est quoi les conditions,
what's all this about?
c'est quoi tout ça ?
And me,
Et moi,
you don't want
tu n'as pas envie
me coming back to you
que je revienne vers toi
trying again.
en essayant.
So,
Donc,
tell me,
dis-moi,
what's the best offer?
quelle est la meilleure offre ?
9.3 million.
9,3 millions.
You just made 300,000.
Vous venez de gagner 300 000.
If your offer today
Si votre offre aujourd'hui
that you're making,
que vous donnez,
The price,
le prix,
it's 9 million,
c'est 9 millions,
and then,
et là,
they'll come back,
il va revenir,
already,
déjà,
someone,
quelqu'un,
you tell them 9 million,
vous lui dites 9 millions,
they'll come back with 8.5 million.
il va revenir avec 8,5 millions.
But,
Mais,
keep that in mind
pensez à ça
and leave yourself some wiggle room.
et à garder du mou.
So,
Donc,
it's really
c'est vraiment
always
toujours
about asking questions
poser des questions
so that,
pour,
if people,
si les gens,
they come back,
ils reviennent,
you can see where they stand.
vous leur voyez la balance.
My price,
Mon prix,
that's it,
c'est ça,
if you want to make me an offer,
si tu veux me proposer,
go ahead.
propose.
But,
Par contre,
I add a condition to it
je le mets dans une condition
where I talk to them,
où je lui fais,
I negotiate,
je négocie,
I explain the whole situation.
je lui explique tout le contexte.
I'm not the only one
Je ne suis pas le seul
making the decision,
à décider,
the price,
le prix,
is the price.
c'est le prix.
If you want to make an offer,
Si tu veux faire une offre,
just give me your offer
tu me fais une offre
with your conditions
avec des conditions
and all that.
et tout ça.
And then,
Et après,
I'll show you
je vais vous montrer
the templates.
les templates.
Are you with me?
Vous êtes avec moi ?
Okay,
Ok,
cool.
cool.
Active negotiation,
La négociation active,
controlled concessions,
concession contrôlée,
strategic silence,
silence stratégique,
handling objections,
gestion des objections,
never give a concession
jamais de concession
without getting something in return.
sans contrepartie.
One day,
Un jour,
I'm selling a house,
je vends une maison,
So,
enfin,
I'm in the middle
je suis en train
of showing a property,
de faire une visite
back when I was an agent,
quand j'étais agent
a real estate agent at the time,
immobilier à l'époque,
and the husband says to me,
et le mari me dit
"I'll never buy this house."
« J'achèterai jamais la maison.
Just like that.
Direct.
No,
Non,
straight up.
direct.
Okay?
Ok ?
But it was exactly
Mais c'était exactement
what he wanted.
ce qu'il voulait.
Because I'd already done
Parce que j'avais fait
the qualification,
la qualification,
etc.
etc.
But he was convinced
Mais il était convaincu
he wasn't going to buy it,
qu'il n'allait pas l'acheter,
and so on.
etc.
But actually,
Et en fait,
when he told me no,
quand il m'a dit non,
it wasn't really no,
ce n'était pas non,
actually.
en fait.
Even if that's exactly
Même si c'est exactement
what he said.
ce qu'il a dit.
Most of you
La plupart d'entre vous
would've said, "Alright,
auraient dit « Bon,
he's done,
lui, terminé,
I'm heading home."
je rentre chez moi.
No, not at all.
Non, pas du tout.
If you know
Si vous savez
that this is exactly
que c'est exactement
the house he needs
la maison qu'il a besoin
for him,
pour lui,
that ticks all his boxes,
qui coche tous ses critères,
you have to sell him that house.
vous devez lui vendre la maison.
And when he says no,
Et quand il dit non,
it's not really no.
ce n'est pas non.
It's no,
C'est non,
"you haven't convinced me enough."
tu ne m'as pas assez convaincu.
No,
Non,
"I'm not ready
je ne suis pas prêt
to buy yet."
à acheter.
Maybe even
Peut-être même
in his head,
dans sa tête,
he's thinking, "Damn,
c'est « Putain,
he's already convinced me,
il m'a déjà convaincu,
but I can't say
mais je ne peux pas dire
yes right away."
oui tout de suite.
So he says no.
Donc il dit non.
Damn,
Putain,
he killed me.
il m'a tué.
I've got nothing to say.
Je n'ai rien à dire.
Well,
Eh bien,
he's telling you no.
il vous dit non.
And there could be
Et il peut se passer
all sorts of reasons.
plein de raisons.
Who here has ever been turned down
Qui s'est déjà fait refouler
and then finally,
et puis finalement,
later on,
après,
you actually got what you wanted?
tu obtiens gain de cause ?
In anything, really.
Dans n'importe quoi d'ailleurs.
It works with
Ça marche avec
meeting people too.
les rencontres humaines.
I could give you
Je peux vous donner
tons of examples,
plein d'exemples,
even personal ones.
perso même.
With my wife,
Avec ma femme,
she told me no.
elle m'a dit non.
Okay,
Ok,
cool.
cool.
Watch me.
Watch me.
Anyway,
Anyway,
are you with me?
vous êtes avec moi ?
So the 'no'
Donc le non
A no isn't a real no.
n'est pas un non.
No is just...
Le non est un...
No,
Non,
it's not over.
ce n'est pas fini.
Obviously,
Bien évidemment,
if people reject you
si les gens vous rejettent
seven times,
pendant sept fois
at some point,
à un moment donné,
okay?
ok ?
Or seven objections,
Ou sept objections,
But you can always come back later.
Mais vous pouvez revenir après.
Closing.
Le closing.
Clarify the terms,
Clarifier les termes,
reduce friction,
réduire les frictions,
create a sense of urgency.
créer un sentiment d'urgence.
If you're here,
Si vous êtes là,
you have what it takes
vous avez le moyen
to close the deal,
de closer le deal,
right,
bon,
we agree
on est d'accord
that if we agree
que si on se met d'accord
on this,
là-dessus,
it's good,
c'est bon,
we're doing the deal.
on fait le deal.
So,
Là,
you grab a sheet of paper,
vous prenez une feuille de papier
and you write out the deal.
et vous écrivez le deal.
Just a plain piece of paper.
Feuille de papier simple.
Martine,
Martine,
can you send me the sheet?
tu peux m'envoyer la feuille ?
Come on,
Viens,
let's go sign with Jacques.
on va signer avec Jacques.
And then,
Et là,
we take it and sign,
on prend et on signe,
we write down the terms and conditions.
on écrit les termes et les conditions.
The price,
Le prix,
the conditions,
les conditions,
the timelines,
les timelines,
etc.
etc.
So,
Et donc,
we agree
on est d'accord
that if we go for it,
que si on se met dessus,
we do the deal.
on fait le deal.
Yes,
Oui,
we agree?
on est d'accord ?
Okay,
Ok,
we shake hands.
on shake hands.
In Switzerland,
En Suisse,
a verbal deal is a deal.
un deal oral est un deal.
When you say it out loud,
Quand vous dites à l'oral,
and you both agree,
on se met d'accord,
that's a deal.
c'est un deal.
You can literally
Vous pouvez littéralement
take that to court
aller vous battre en justice
if you need to.
contre ça.
I know most people
Je sais que la plupart des gens,
need a written contract,
ils ont besoin d'un contrat écrit,
but at some point,
mais à un moment donné,
there are people
il y a des gens
who still keep their word.
qui ont encore de la parole.
There are people,
Il y a des gens,
you shake their hand,
vous siérez leurs mains,
and you just know they'll come back
vous le savez qu'ils vont revenir
and they'll make the deal.
et qu'ils vont faire un deal.
So,
Donc,
take advantage of that too
profitez-en aussi
and align yourself
pour vous aligner
with those kinds of people.
avec ces gens-là.
Alright?
D'accord ?
So,
Donc,
try to close deals that way.
essayez de closer comme ça.
the three major mistakes.
les trois erreurs majeures.
First,
Un,
talking price too soon.
parler de prix trop tôt.
When you don't know
Quand vous ne connaissez pas
the real reasons for the sale,
les raisons réelles de la vente,
when you don't have
que vous n'avez pas
the full picture,
toutes les perspectives,
you shouldn't talk about price.
il ne faut pas parler de prix.
Now,
Là,
if the person,
si la personne,
they come,
elle vient
or the real estate agent,
ou l'agent immobilier,
or whoever,
il vient
in any negotiation,
dans quelle négociation
the person brings up price,
la personne vous parle de prix,
okay, let's talk price,
on va parler du prix,
but me,
mais moi,
I still don't get
je n'ai toujours pas compris
why you want to sell.
pourquoi vous voulez vendre.
Me,
Moi,
I'm not here
je ne suis pas là
to waste my time.
pour perdre mon temps.
I'm really interested,
Je suis très intéressé,
but,
par contre,
help me out here,
éclairez-moi,
what's the real price
quel est le vrai prix
that you actually want?
que vous voulez,
because right now,
parce que là,
your price at 10 million,
votre prix à 10 millions,
it's just crazy.
c'est insensé.
You know very well,
Vous savez très bien,
the market will only give you 6,
le marché vous en donne 6,
Me,
Moi,
maybe I'm willing
je suis peut-être prêt
to go a bit higher.
à monter plus.
But,
Par contre,
10,
10,
that's a no-go.
c'est mort.
You see,
Vous voyez,
that's just an example.
c'est un exemple.
So,
Donc,
we'll talk about the price later
on va parler du prix après
and then,
et après,
you can bounce back on the rest.
vous rebondissez sur le reste.
OK?
OK ?
When you have someone
Quand vous avez quelqu'un
who tells you,
qui vous dise,
OK,
OK,
but,
par contre,
I want the money right away
je veux l'argent tout de suite
or there's another concession,
ou il y a une autre concession,
try to negotiate differently.
et essayer de négocier différemment.
I explained it downstairs,
Je l'ai expliqué en bas,
but I think it's good
mais je pense que c'est bien
to explain it to you here,
que je vous l'explique ici,
kind of like a negotiation
un petit peu une négociation
we're having right now.
qu'on est en train d'avoir là.
We're selling a house.
On est en train de vendre une maison.
OK?
OK ?
48.9 million dirhams.
48,9 millions de dirhams.
Listed.
Listé.
The real estate agent,
L'agent immobilier,
he comes to me and says,
il vient et me dit,
"I've got someone who wants to buy the house,
j'ai quelqu'un qui veut acheter la maison,
but they want a payment plan."
mais il veut un plan de paiement.
I say,
Je dis,
"We don't do payment plans."
on ne fait pas de plan de paiement.
But,
Par contre,
if he's ready to pay
s'il est prêt à payer
50% right away
50% tout de suite
and 50% by the end of the year,
et 50% d'ici la fin de l'année,
at a higher price,
à un prix plus élevé,
maybe I can offer that,
peut-être que je peux le proposer,
I can work it out with the seller.
je peux gérer avec le vendeur.
OK,
OK,
I'll get back to you,
je reviens vers toi,
I'll talk to him about it.
j'en parle.
OK.
OK.
48.9,
48,9,
we're coming back,
on revient,
we're agreeing
on est en train de se mettre d'accord
on 51.
sur 51.
We'll see,
On verra,
I'm not convinced,
ça ne me dit,
it's not closed yet.
il n'est pas encore closé.
But hey,
Mais bon,
listen up,
écoutez bien,
51,
51,
that's still
c'est quand même
over a million dollars more.
plus d'un million de dollars de plus.
Right?
D'accord ?
He tells me,
Il me dit,
yeah,
oui,
but on the other hand,
mais par contre,
we need to take the villa off the market
il faut sortir la villa du marché
for two months.
pendant deux mois.
I say,
Je dis,
but me,
mais moi,
I'm not taking the villa off the market
je ne vais pas sortir la villa du marché
for two months.
pendant deux mois.
Unless,
Sauf si,
you give me a million dirhams,
tu me donnes un million de dirhams,
250,000 dollars,
250 000 dollars,
right now,
tout de suite,
that you're ready to lose
que tu es prêt à perdre
so I can take the house off the market.
pour que je sorte la maison.
Let me get back to you.
Laisse-moi revenir.
He comes back,
Il revient,
we agree
on se met d'accord
on 850,000 dirhams.
sur 850 000 dirhams.
to take the house off the market
pour sortir la maison du marché
for two months.
pendant deux mois.
That means,
Ça veut dire que,
yeah,
oui,
200,000 euros.
200 000 euros.
So that means by the end of April,
Ça veut dire qu'à la fin du mois d'avril,
so now,
donc là,
basically,
en gros,
before signing,
avant de signer,
I've got a check,
j'ai un chèque,
not a regular check,
pas un chèque normal,
a cashier's check.
un chèque de banque.
I tell him,
Je lui dis,
you give me the cashier's check,
tu me donnes le chèque de banque,
we sign the contract,
on signe le contrat,
I take the villa off the market
je sors la villa du marché
until the end of April.
jusqu'à fin avril.
You have until the end of April
Tu as jusqu'à fin avril
to let me know
pour me dire
if you want to buy the house or not.
si tu veux acheter la maison ou pas.
If you say no,
si tu refuses,
we part ways,
on se quitte,
no hard feelings,
bons amis,
and I keep the check.
je garde le chèque.
That's in the contract.
C'est dans le contrat.
But seriously,
Mais bon,
you do agree
vous êtes bien d'accord
that someone who's willing
que quelqu'un qui est prêt
to put down money like that
à mettre de l'argent comme ça
on the table,
sur la table,
because he can't be there
parce qu'il ne peut pas être là-bas
in person to see the house,
physiquement pour voir la maison,
he must really
il a quand même
seriously want to buy it.
superbement envie de l'acheter.
I gave you the quick version.
Je vous ai fait la version rapide.
He did three tours,
Il a fait trois visites,
videos,
vidéos,
Zoom calls,
zoom,
all that stuff,
machin,
but he just can't travel.
il ne peut pas se déplacer.
He really wants to buy it,
Il a vraiment envie de l'acheter,
so he's seriously
donc il est vraiment en train
for wanting to come.
de vouloir venir.
Alright?
D'accord ?
I'll keep going.
Je continue.
So,
Du coup,
he tells us,
il nous dit,
this is live,
c'est live,
it happened two weeks ago.
ça date d'il y a deux semaines.
Let me set the scene for you
Je vous mets dans l'ambiance
for the negotiation.
de la négociation.
We're here to talk about negotiation.
On est là pour parler de négociation.
I'm going to show you
Je vais vous montrer
how detailed you can get
jusqu'où on peut granulariser
with an offer
une proposition
instead of just saying
plutôt que de dire
me,
moi,
lots of payment options,
plein de paiement,
I don't do that.
je ne fais pas.
No.
Non.
Wait,
Attends,
let's talk about the terms.
on va parler des conditions.
Are you following me?
Vous me suivez là ?
So,
Du coup,
I tell him,
je lui dis,
okay,
ok,
end of the month,
fin du mois,
You tell me
tu me dis
if you want to buy,
si tu veux acheter,
per year,
par an,
you give me 50%.
tu me donnes 50%.
at the end of the month,
à la fin du mois,
you move into the house,
tu emménages dans la maison,
but if by December 25th,
mais si au 25 décembre,
you don't pay
tu ne payes pas
the other 50%,
les autres 50%,
you lose your 50%,
tu perds tes 50%,
you have to leave the house
tu dois partir de la maison
and I keep the place.
et je garde la baraque.
Okay.
Ok.
So,
Donc,
it's really
c'est vraiment
who wants the house.
qui veut la maison.
Are we good with that or not?
On est d'accord ou pas ?
So now,
Donc là,
basically,
en gros,
let's see.
on va voir.
I've already seen the check,
J'ai vu le chèque déjà,
we got the check,
on a reçu le chèque,
we'll see if it actually gets signed or not.
on verra si ça va signer ou pas.
And so,
Et du coup,
what is it?
c'est quoi ?
I'm free money,
Je suis free money,
I'm a free option.
je suis free option.
I make 200,000 bucks
Je gagne 200 000 balles
just for giving someone the option
juste pour donner l'option
to buy.
à quelqu'un d'acheter.
That,
Ça,
again,
encore une fois,
we're talking about selling a house.
on est sur la vente d'une maison.
For you,
Pour vous,
you can work it
vous pouvez le travailler
in different ways.
de différentes manières.
So,
Donc,
get creative with it.
soyez créatif par rapport à ça.
Okay.
Ok.
Part 2,
Partie 2,
the 10 qualities
les 10 qualités
of a good negotiator.
du bon négociateur.
So,
Alors,
this,
ça,
is super important too.
c'est très important aussi.
Win,
Win,
lose.
lose.
So,
Donc,
I win,
je gagne,
you lose.
tu perds.
Not good.
Pas bon.
That doesn't work in the long run.
Ça ne marche pas dans le long terme.
It just won't work.
Ça ne marchera pas.
So,
Donc,
I win,
je gagne,
you lose.
tu perds.
That means,
Ça veut dire que,
really,
vraiment,
there's an imbalance
il y a une asymétrie
between the fact that
entre le fait que
you,
vous,
you really gained something
vous avez vraiment gagné quelque chose
and the other person,
et la personne,
you're kind of ripping them off a bit.
vous êtes en train de l'arnaquer un petit peu.
Basically.
En gros.
Careful,
Attention,
there are some really great deals.
il y a des très bons deals.
You're in a win-win situation
Vous êtes sur du win-win
as soon as
à partir du moment donné
the other person,
et la personne,
it's a win for them too.
c'est un win.
But for it to be a loss
Mais pour que ce soit un lose
and for the...
et que la...
You see,
Vous voyez,
that's not good.
c'est pas bon.
The lose-win,
Le lose win,
obviously,
bien évidemment,
we don't go for that.
on n'y va pas.
Okay.
Ok.
The win-win,
Le win-win,
that's good,
c'est bien,
but try to find the win-win-win.
mais essayez de trouver le win-win-win.
So what's a win-win-win?
C'est quoi le win-win-win ?
A win-win-win,
Le win-win-win,
is when
c'est quand
I win,
je gagne,
well,
enfin,
you win,
tu gagnes,
I win,
je gagne
and together we win even more
et nous gagnons encore plus
because when you add it up,
parce que la somme des deux
we end up doing way more.
fait qu'on va faire beaucoup plus.
On your side,
De ton côté,
you see what I mean?
vous voyez ce que je veux dire ?
That,
Ça,
that works in every partnership,
ça marche dans tous les partenariats,
every negotiation,
les négociations,
and so on.
etc.
Try to see what you can find
Essayez de voir ce que vous pouvez trouver
at the ultimate level with this.
en niveau ultime là-dessus.
So,
Donc,
let me give you an example.
je vous donne un exemple.
Someone,
Quelqu'un,
a marchand de biens,
un marchand de biens,
I was talking to him not long ago,
je lui parlais il n'y a pas longtemps,
he locked in a deal.
il a sécurisé un deal.
They came to an agreement
Ils se sont mis d'accord
between the investor putting up the money,
entre l'investisseur qui investit,
the project leader with the project,
le porteur du projet qui a le projet
and he makes the deal happen.
et il fait le deal.
And this guy,
Et lui,
he says,
il dit,
since his son wants to join him
comme son fils veut le rejoindre
in the marchand de biens business,
dans la partie de marchand de biens,
he tells him,
il lui dit,
you know what?
c'est quoi ?
On top of that,
En plus de ça,
we do the deal,
on fait le deal,
I'll help your son out.
je vais aider ton fils.
I'll show him
Je vais lui montrer
what being a marchand de biens is all about,
ce que c'est d'être marchand de biens
and I'll show him
et je vais lui montrer
how to do the whole thing,
de faire le truc,
and so on.
etc.
The investor
L'investisseur
who's older
qui est âgé
is really happy
est très content
to see
de voir
that his son
que son fils
is going to come
va venir
manage the deal
gérer l'opération
and get mentored
et se faire mentorer
by a marchand de biens.
par un marchand de biens.
It's a win-win,
C'est un deal win,
win, and win.
win et win.
And that,
Et ça,
can only happen
il peut arriver uniquement
when you actually know
quand vous connaissez
what really motivates people,
les motivations réelles des gens,
what's going on behind the scenes,
qu'est-ce qu'ils ont derrière,
when you care about their family,
que vous intéressez à leur famille,
what they're planning to do
qu'est-ce qu'ils vont faire
over the next 5-10 years,
sur les 5-10 prochaines années,
where they're at
où est-ce qu'ils en sont
in their life,
dans leur vie,
and so on.
etc.
Are you following me or not?
Vous me suivez ou pas ?
Same thing,
Pareil,
an eco-friendly type.
un écolo.
An eco-friendly type,
Un écolo,
do a deal with an eco-friendly person,
faites un deal avec un écolo,
you know they're into being green,
vous savez qu'il est écolo,
there's a bonus,
il y a une prime,
at some point,
à un moment donné,
I'm only going to do solar panels,
je ne vais faire que des panneaux solaires,
I'm only going to do eco stuff,
je ne vais faire que des trucs,
we're going to make it an eco-friendly project.
on va faire un projet écologique.
And you go for it,
Et vous le faites,
obviously.
bien évidemment.
And right there,
Et bien là,
it's a win-win-win,
c'est du win, win, win,
plus you create
vous créez en plus
an even bigger alpha.
un alpha superieur.
Do you realize what you're
Vous savez ce que vous êtes
actually doing?
en train de faire ?
Not only is it good
Non seulement c'est bien
for everyone,
pour tout le monde,
but on top of that,
mais en plus de ça,
it puts you way ahead of
ça vous met loin devant
the rest of the competition,
la compétition des autres,
who won't even go there.
qui ne vont pas venir là-dessus.
People are way too focused on price.
Les gens sont trop orientés prix.
There are people,
Il y a des gens,
they couldn't care less
ils ne s'en battent
about money.
de l'argent.
People want to do deals
Ils veulent faire des deals
with people they like,
avec des gens qu'ils aiment,
with people they vibe with.
avec des gens avec qui ils peuvent.
Me, I don't do business anymore
Moi, je ne fais plus d'affaires
or work with partners,
ou avec des partenaires,
I don't bring people on board anymore
je ne recrute plus des gens
if I don't feel like...
à qui je n'ai pas envie de...
If I know I can't
Si je sais que je ne peux pas
have a conversation with you
avoir une conversation avec toi
and go out to dinner with you
et aller dîner avec toi
for two hours and all that,
pendant deux heures et tout
because you were annoying,
parce que tu étais relou,
I'm just not interested.
ça ne m'intéresse pas.
So that's the level
Donc, c'est dans ce niveau-là
you need to reach.
que vous devez arriver.
Who wants to deal with
Qui a envie de gérer
and work with people
et de gérer et de travailler
who are negative,
avec des gens qui sont négatifs,
only focused on...?
orientés que sur...
Am I right or not?
On est d'accord ou pas ?
You want to do deals
Vous voulez faire des deals
with people you really like,
avec des gens que vous kiffez,
yes or no?
oui ou non ?
That's why
Voilà, c'est pour ça
communities like this
que les communautés comme ça
are important.
sont importantes.
So, let's keep going.
Donc, on enchaîne.
Listening.
L'écoute.
Listening isn't the same
Écouter, ce n'est pas pareil
as just hearing.
qu'entendre.
Read between the lines.
Lire entre les lignes.
Pick up on what's not being said.
Comprendre les non-dits.
These are skills you develop
Compétences qui s'acquiert
over time.
avec le temps.
Did you know
Est-ce que vous savez
that listening
que l'écoute,
is actually a skill?
c'est une compétence ?
Did you know that?
Vous le saviez, ça ?
Okay.
Ok.
So why don't we use it?
Alors, pourquoi on ne l'applique pas ?
Why are there people...
Pourquoi il y a des gens...
I'll give you,
Je vais vous donner après,
I think I have some stats,
je pense que j'ai des chiffres,
I hope.
j'espère.
I talked about it with the others.
J'en ai parlé aux autres.
Listening is different from hearing.
Écouter, c'est différent d'entendre.
We get interrupted
On est interrompus
every 17 seconds.
toutes les 17 secondes.
So that's why
Donc, c'est pour ça
I'm using a timer.
que je fais le timer.
I'm starting the timer
Je donne le timer
so you have one minute
pour que vous ayez une minute
to introduce yourself
pour pouvoir vous présenter
and then,
et qu'ensuite,
the other person introduces themselves
l'autre personne se présente
the other person introduces themselves.
l'autre personne se présente.
And in five minutes,
Et en cinq minutes,
who used the timer
qui a utilisé le timer
during the lunch break?
pendant la pause-déj ?
Not yet.
Pas encore.
Okay.
Ok.
No one's taking action
On ne passe pas à l'action
in this community.
dans cette communauté.
or maybe they're all downstairs,
ou ils sont tous en bas
the advanced ones.
les avancés, là.
I asked the question,
J'ai posé la question,
there were a few more
il y avait un peu plus
hands raised,
de mains levées,
but it still wasn't
mais ce n'était pas non plus
crazy.
la folie.
Why am I bothering you
Pourquoi je vous embête
with the timer?
avec le timer ?
Because I want to give you
Parce que je veux vous donner
the opportunity
l'opportunité
to meet
de rencontrer
the partner,
l'associé,
the investor,
l'investisseur,
the project leader
le porteur de projet
who's hiding out in this room.
qui se cache dans cette salle.
But if today,
Mais si aujourd'hui,
you're here
vous êtes là
and you start talking,
et vous commencez à parler,
you're in a group
vous êtes dans un groupe
of three or four,
de trois, quatre,
and you start
et vous commencez
introducing yourself,
à vous présenter,
there's always one guy,
il y en a un,
he cuts you off
il vous coupe la parole
after 17 seconds.
au bout de 17 secondes.
Has that never happened to you?
Ça ne vous est jamais arrivé ?
There's a guy,
Il y a un mec,
he shows up,
il arrive,
just barges in like that,
il se pointe comme ça,
he's there,
il est là,
bam,
bam,
he grabs the spotlight,
il prend le truc,
the other guy,
l'autre,
starts talking
il commence à parler
with him and everything,
avec lui et tout,
You missed your chance.
vous avez perdu votre truc
So, where do we go from here?
et on va où ?
You lost the opportunity.
Vous avez perdu l'opportunité.
Who's ever found themselves
Qui est déjà retrouvé
in a situation like that,
dans une situation comme ça,
super frustrated
hyper frustrée
because you couldn't finish
de ne pas pouvoir finir
what you wanted to say,
ce qu'il veut dire
because there are people
parce qu'il y a des gens
who are there,
qui sont là,
just talking about their lives.
qui racontent leur life.
Same thing,
Pareil,
for you shy people.
vous les timides.
Me,
Moi,
speaking for a minute,
parler une minute,
right away,
hors de suite,
no way.
hors question.
Shy folks,
Les timides,
you also need
vous devez aussi
to speak up.
vous exprimer.
So,
Donc,
it's important.
c'est important.
listening,
écouter,
that's important too,
c'est important,
It's a skill.
c'est une compétence.
Listening,
Écouter,
it's the words,
c'est les mots,
the looks,
les regards,
the intentions,
les intentions,
the real reasons.
les vraies raisons.
Information,
L'information,
is the most important asset
c'est l'actif le plus important
when you're negotiating.
en tant que négociateur.
So,
Donc,
if you're talking,
si vous parlez,
you've already lost, in my book.
vous avez perdu pour moi.
When you start negotiating,
Quand on rentre en négociation,
the very first thing
la première des choses
to do,
à faire,
is ask questions
c'est de poser des questions
so that people
pour que les gens
answer you.
vous répondent.
Because that's the only way
Parce qu'il n'y a que comme ça
you'll find out
qu'on va savoir
what makes them tick,
qu'est-ce qui les fait tiquer,
what they really want to do.
qu'est-ce qu'ils ont envie de faire.
But you have to do it.
Mais il faut le faire.
You'll see,
Vous allez voir,
it's going to be tough
ça va être dur
for some of you.
pour certains d'entre vous.
Honestly,
Franchement,
I'm challenging you right now
je vous challenge dès maintenant
during the networking breaks,
pour les pauses networking,
you'll see.
vous allez voir.
Around you,
Autour de vous,
the people who never stop
les gens qui ne s'arrêtent pas
talking,
de parler,
blah blah and all that,
machin et tout,
it's not necessarily...
c'est pas forcément...
You see,
Vous voyez,
you really need to master this.
il faut bien maîtriser ça.
So,
Donc,
let me give you an example.
je donne un exemple.
Listening,
L'écoute,
a skill,
compétence,
let me give you an example.
je donne un exemple.
So this,
Donc ça,
is Erin
c'est Erin
sending me a message,
qui m'envoie un message,
who's one of our agents
qui est une de nos agents
at Bonaparte in Dubai.
chez Bonaparte à Dubaï.
So here,
Donc là,
she says to me
elle me dit
"Hi Jean-Guillaume,
« Salut Jean-Guillaume,
It's Erin from Bonaparte,
c'est Erin de Bonaparte,
I've got an investor
j'ai un investisseur
who's looking to invest
qui cherche à déployer
between 25 and 50 million dirhams,
entre 25 et 50 millions de dirhams,
so that's between 6 and 15 million dollars,
donc entre 6 et 15 millions de dollars,
for a project
dans le cadre
redevelopment deal.
de redéveloppement de projet.
I'm going to show him the tours,
Je vais lui montrer les visites,
Albarari,
Albarari,
the quality,
la qualité,
the finishes.
les finitions.
I'd like to set up
J'aimerais mettre
a call with you
un call avec toi
to talk about
pour discuter
strategy options.
des options de stratégie.
I know
Je sais que
you're out of the country,
tu es à l'extérieur du pays,
but we can still
mais on peut quand même
set up a call,
mettre un call,
etc.
etc.
That's it.
Voilà.
Alright.
Bon.
She just got here.
Elle vient d'arriver.
She's doing her job well
Elle fait bien son travail
because it's a guy
parce que c'est un mec
super qualified.
hyper qualifié.
But right now I don't have enough
Mais je n'ai pas assez
information today
d'informations aujourd'hui
to know if I'm the one
pour savoir si c'est à moi
who should talk to him, etc.
de lui parler, etc.
So my question is,
Donc ma question,
what's his profile?
c'est quoi le profil ?
What's his timeline?
Quel est son délai ?
When does he want his return
Il veut quand son retour
on investment?
sur investissement ?
How much of a return
C'est combien le retour
on investment
sur investissement
is he expecting?
auquel il s'attend ?
Is the money,
Est-ce que l'argent,
already available
il est déjà disponible
over there on site,
sur place là-bas,
is he ready to pull the trigger?
il est prêt à shooter ?
So then,
Et du coup,
she sets up a call for me,
elle me met un call,
so I take the opportunity
du coup j'en profite
to train her.
pour la former.
So,
Du coup,
when we do the call,
quand on fait le call,
I start things off.
je commence.
So the one leading the way,
Donc celui qui mène la danse,
he's the one setting the timer.
c'est celui qui pose le timer.
So, hello,
Donc bonjour,
here we are,
on est là,
we've got about thirty minutes.
on a une trentaine de minutes.
I'd like you to take the time
J'aimerais vous prenez le temps
to explain this
de vous exprimer ça
in five minutes.
en cinq minutes.
I'll introduce myself
Je vais me présenter
afterwards, in five minutes too,
ensuite en cinq minutes
and then we'll take
et ensuite on prendra
twenty minutes
vingt minutes
for Q&A.
pour les questions réponses.
Sound good?
Ça vous va ?
Alright, go ahead,
Bam, allez-y,
I'm listening,
je vous écoute,
I'm starting the timer.
je mets le timer.
Boom.
Boum.
The guy,
Le mec,
he introduces himself.
il se présente.
Actually, there are two of them.
Ils sont deux d'ailleurs.
I realize
Je m'aperçois
that not only
que non seulement
does he want to do deals
il veut faire des deals
in the United Arab Emirates,
aux Émirats Arabes Unis,
they want to do deals
qu'ils veulent faire des deals
in France,
en France,
that they have a potential
qu'ils ont un réseau
distribution network.
de distribution potentiel.
And now,
Et là,
we're really starting to get into
on commence à rentrer
a whole different
vraiment dans
kind of conversation.
d'autres types de discussions.
But they gave me
Mais ils m'ont donné
their timeline,
leur délai,
their ROI,
leur ROI,
the funds they have available,
les fonds disponibles
and those funds,
et ces fonds,
they're not available
ils ne sont pas disponibles
for another six months.
avant six mois.
Am I in a rush
Est-ce que j'ai une urgence
right in the middle of a roadshow
en plein roadshow
to work,
de bosser,
to take the call?
de prendre le call ?
You see what I mean?
Vous voyez ce que je veux dire ?
So you need to gather
Donc vous devez prendre
information,
de l'information
and that's
et ça,
about listening,
c'est l'écoute,
so asking questions.
donc poser des questions.
Are you following me or not?
Vous me suivez ou pas ?
There you go.
Voilà.
Time management,
Gestion du temps,
we're back to it.
on en revient.
Structure your meetings.
Structurez vos meetings.
When you set up meetings
Quand vous faites des meetings
for 15 minutes
de 15 minutes
to 30 minutes,
à 30 minutes,
that's perfect.
c'est très bien.
You talked to someone
Vous avez parlé avec quelqu'un
for the first time?
pour la première fois ?
Me,
Moi,
every single time,
systématiquement,
depending on the person's profile,
en fonction du profil
depending on who they are,
de la personne,
it's 15 minutes.
c'est 15 minutes.
15 minutes!
15 minutes !
Sometimes,
Des fois,
it can be 30 minutes
ça peut être 30 minutes
if the person,
si la personne,
if I see there's
je vois qu'il y a
real interest.
un vrai intérêt.
But if someone wants to talk to me,
Mais quelqu'un qui veut me parler,
first,
déjà,
I want to know why.
je veux savoir pourquoi.
What's their...
C'est quoi son...
That's right!
Eh oui !
Otherwise,
Sinon,
we spend our lives
on passe notre vie
just talking to people,
à parler avec des gens,
basically.
en fait.
But here,
Là,
let me remind you
je vous rappelle
we're here
qu'on est là
to go after
pour aller chercher
tens of millions.
les dizaines de millions.
Of course,
Bien évidemment,
some of you
certains d'entre vous
might just want
veulent peut-être
to stop at one or two,
s'arrêter à un ou deux,
I don't know,
je ne sais pas,
and that's totally fine.
il n'y a pas de problème.
really far,
très loin,
really fast,
très vite,
with as many people as possible
avec un maximum de gens
and I also have to
et je me dois aussi
be the best.
d'être le meilleur.
So,
Donc,
time management,
la gestion du temps,
we have to nail it.
on est obligé d'y arriver.
Billionaires,
Les milliardaires,
they have five-minute meetings
ils ont des rendez-vous
Just five minutes.
de 5 minutes.
Trust me, if you're not ready,
Crois-moi que si t'es pas préparé,
you're getting your head chopped off.
tu te fais décapiter.
But sometimes, meetings last 15 to 30 minutes,
Mais 15 minutes à 30 minutes,
the in-person ones,
les rendez-vous physiques,
some of them,
il y en a,
they've gone on for two hours.
ça a duré 2 heures.
Yeah,
Ouais,
don't worry,
t'inquiète,
come on,
viens,
let's meet at the office,
rendez-vous au bureau,
we'll take off.
on décrole.
Okay,
Ok,
sure,
d'accord,
they show up at 10 a.m.,
ils arrivent à 10 heures,
noon,
midi,
lunch break,
pause déj,
a little alcohol,
un peu d'alcool,
your meeting,
ton meeting,
it's already lasted four hours.
il a duré 4 heures déjà.
Total chaos.
Flingue et totale.
There's a time for everything.
Il y a des temps pour tout.
There's a meeting,
Il y a un rendez-vous,
10 a.m.,
10 heures,
10 AM to 1 PM,
10 heures à 13 heures,
10 AM to 10:30 AM,
10 heures à 10h30
or 10 AM to 11 AM,
ou 10 heures à 11 heures
and then after that,
et puis après,
ciao,
ciao,
I do an hour,
je fais une heure
and if you need to meet again,
et puis si vous devez le revoir,
actually,
au contraire,
it's better to have
il vaut mieux faire
a quick meeting,
un rendez-vous rapide
just to get to know each other,
de découverte
and then do a follow-up call,
et faire un follow-up call
or grab an informal lunch.
ou un déjeuner informel.
Are you following me or not?
Vous me suivez ou pas ?
With that person,
Avec la personne,
the following week,
la semaine d'après,
you build a relationship
vous créez une relation
with people.
avec les gens.
So,
Donc,
keep that in mind.
pensez à ça.
me,
moi,
I always do
je fais toujours
a formal meeting,
un rendez-vous formel
and then I follow up,
et j'enchaîne
with an informal meeting
avec un rendez-vous informel
or an informal meeting
ou un rendez-vous informel
and I buy
et j'enchète
with a formal meeting
avec un rendez-vous formel
because I want to show
parce que je veux montrer
people the scale of things.
aux gens la dimension.
When they see me,
Quand ils me voient,
they don't see anything around me,
ils ne voient rien autour de moi,
they haven't seen the teams,
ils n'ont pas vu les équipes,
they haven't seen the group,
ils n'ont pas vu le groupe,
they haven't seen the credibility
ils n'ont pas vu la crédibilité
that's behind it
qu'il y a derrière
depending on what you want to do.
selon ce que vous voulez faire.
So,
Donc,
I like to meet them at the office
j'aime bien les recevoir au bureau
where there's credibility.
là où il y a de la crédibilité.
I also like to meet them
J'aime bien les recevoir
outside
à l'extérieur
to build a relationship,
pour pouvoir créer une relation,
break the bread
break the bread
as they say,
comme on dit,
so eat together,
donc manger ensemble,
and so on.
etc.
as the investor, it's me
investisseur que c'est moi
who handles things directly
qui traite en direct
and then,
et ensuite,
I start picking up my phone
je commence à prendre mon téléphone
and calling her
et à l'appeler
so she gets used to it
qu'elle commence à s'y habituer
and after that,
et après,
you pick up the phone,
vous prenez le téléphone,
that's how
c'est comme ça
you build relationships
que vous créez des relations
with people.
avec les gens.
Alright?
D'accord ?
So,
Donc,
another thing,
aussi un autre,
I don't know how
je ne sais pas comment
we're going to manage this,
on va y arriver là,
but hey,
mais bon,
it's no big deal.
c'est pas grave.
We're on the second part,
On est sur la deuxième partie,
the first part,
première partie,
it's crazy.
c'est abusé.
I'll have to do it later
Il faut que je le ferai après
in a small meeting afterwards
en petite réunion derrière
if we don't have time
si on n'a pas le temps
to finish everything
de finir tout
at the end of the event.
à la fin de l'événement.
So,
Donc,
when someone talks there too,
quand quelqu'un y parle en plus,
in the first five minutes,
dans les cinq premières minutes,
if he spoke in two minutes,
s'il a parlé en deux minutes,
you know,
vous savez,
what does that tell you?
qu'est-ce que ça vous dit ?
He's structured,
Il est structuré,
organized,
organisé,
or he just doesn't like talking,
ou il n'aime pas parler,
logical,
logique,
numbers.
chiffre.
That's not the same kind of presentation
Ce n'est pas la même présentation
I'm going to give him.
que je vais lui donner.
For him,
Lui,
I'm not going to talk to him
je ne vais pas lui parler
about storytelling,
du storytelling,
or whatever,
de machin,
no,
non,
it's just, hello,
c'est bonjour,
we did X,
on a fait X,
here's what we're offering,
voilà ce qu'on propose,
here's Z.
voilà Z.
Damn,
Putain,
he's going to be happy
il va être content
because he's an analytical type.
parce que c'est un analytique.
The other one,
L'autre,
a five-minute presentation,
présentation de cinq minutes,
where they just told me their whole life story?
comment ça me racontait sa life ?
It was all over the place.
Ça part dans tous les sens.
Storytelling,
Storytelling,
emotion,
émotion,
that's just how I am,
je suis comme ça moi,
at my core.
à la base.
I'm more of an emotional type,
J'ai plus un profil émotion,
I like telling stories,
je raconte des histoires,
as you can see.
vous le voyez.
But I'm analytical too,
Mais je suis analytique,
I love data as well.
j'aime la data aussi.
When I talk with Guillaume,
Quand je parle avec Guillaume,
it's not the same conversation
ce n'est pas la même conversation
as when I talk with Yann,
que quand je parle avec Yann,
as when I talk with Benoît,
que quand je parle avec Benoît,
you have to try to adapt.
on doit essayer de s'adapter.
It takes time.
Ça met du temps.
But someone who takes a long position,
Mais quelqu'un qui fait une position longue,
storytelling,
storytelling,
they're driven by emotion.
il est lié sur l'émotion.
So in my presentation,
Dans ma présentation,
I'm going to focus more on,
je vais plus l'orienter,
storytelling,
storytelling,
emotion,
émotion,
and I'll wrap up with the numbers.
et je vais finir avec les chiffres.
Are you with me?
Vous êtes avec moi ?
Some of you are falling asleep,
Il y en a certains qui dorment,
I don't know if I should clap
je ne sais pas si je dois claquer
or just do nothing,
ou rien faire,
but anyway.
mais bref.
Maybe I'm staring at you all too much,
Peut-être que je vous regarde tous trop,
actually.
en fait.
Just so you know, I'm watching all of you.
Sachez que je vous regarde tous.
Like this,
Comme ça,
you're being judged.
vous êtes jugés.
You, sir,
Vous, monsieur,
don't pretend...
ne faites pas le...
I saw you.
Je vous ai vus.
I'm going to stomp my foot.
Je vais taper du pied.
This is for you, okay?
C'est pour vous, hein ?
Do you find yourself boring?
Vous vous trouvez boring ?
Boring?
Ennuyant ?
No?
Non ?
Alright, fine.
Bon, OK.
Let's just say you're tired.
On va dire que vous êtes fatigués.
Me, I've got jet lag,
Moi, j'ai le jet lag,
I slept two hours,
je dormis deux heures,
I'm wiped out,
je suis éclaté,
But I'm here.
mais je suis là.
OK?
OK ?
So please, make an effort.
Donc, faites un effort, s'il vous plaît.
Thanks.
Merci.
Alright.
OK.
How many slides do we have left?
On est à combien de slides, là ?
Yeah, that's not amazing, is it?
Oh, c'est pas fou, hein ?
Not great right now.
C'est pas fou, là.
So I'm going to go really fast here.
Alors, je vais aller très vite, là.
Let's go,
On en voit,
we'll do a quick session.
on va faire une petite session vite.
So grab your phones,
Donc, vous prenez vos appareils photos,
we're going to go snap, snap, snap, OK?
on va faire tac, tac, tac, OK ?
Just know you're being judged all the time,
Donc, sachez que vous êtes jugés tout le temps,
your look,
votre look,
the clothes you wear,
vos habits que vous portez,
your hairstyle,
vous êtes coiffés,
if you're clean-shaven,
rasés,
if you have a beard,
barbus,
if you wear rings,
bagués,
if you have a ring.
vous avez une bague.
You're being judged,
Vous êtes jugés,
people are judging you.
on vous juge.
If you're single,
Vous êtes célibataire,
People are judging you all the time.
Les gens vous jugent tout le temps.
Me, I just tell it like it is.
Moi, je vous dis les choses.
Are you fit?
Vous êtes fit ?
You're not fit.
Vous n'êtes pas fit.
Do you smell good?
Vous sentez ?
You don't smell.
Vous ne sentez pas.
Do you drink?
Vous buvez ?
Do you smoke?
Vous fumez ?
What?
Quoi ?
How often?
La fréquence ?
Do you have watches?
Vous avez des montres ?
Do you have cars?
Vous avez des voitures ?
Handbag?
Sac à main ?
Shoes?
Chaussures ?
The first time someone shakes your hand?
La première fois qu'on vous serre la main ?
Handshake?
Handshake ?
Are you being judged?
Vous êtes jugés ?
Are we being judged?
On est jugés ?
We're all being judged non-stop.
On est tous jugés non-stop.
So, why does this matter in negotiation?
Donc, pourquoi c'est important en négociation ?
Because depending on who you're negotiating with,
Parce que selon avec qui vous négociez,
it matters.
ça a de l'importance.
Tomorrow, you're there,
Demain, vous êtes là,
you're trying to raise 1 million, 2 million,
vous cherchez à lever 1 million, 2 millions,
and you show up all casual in a t-shirt,
et vous arrivez comme ça à décontracter les t-shirts,
the thingamajig, the whatever.
le baguine, le machin.
I'm telling you,
Je vous garantis,
depending on the investor,
selon l'investisseur,
you just won't close the deal.
vous ne le closez pas en fait.
So, you have to adapt too.
Donc, il faut aussi s'adapter.
Now, I know these days,
Alors, je sais que maintenant,
nowadays,
de nos jours,
all the startup guys,
les startuppers,
all back there,
tous là derrière,
in their t-shirts,
le t-shirt,
whatever,
machin,
me, I'm not a fan.
moi, je ne suis pas fan.
But hey, at the same time,
Mais bon, en même temps,
I'm in charge of fundraising
je m'occupe du fundraising
and raising capital.
et de la levée de fonds.
Obviously.
Forcément.
But some people,
Mais certains,
if tomorrow,
si demain,
you have a client
vous avez un client
or a guy
ou un gars
you meet
que vous voyez
who's always super sharp,
qui est toujours impeccable sur lui,
and you want to buy his house,
vous voulez lui acheter sa maison,
make an effort.
faites un effort.
Go fix your hair,
Allez vous coiffer,
Shave,
rasez,
do whatever you want.
faites ce que vous voulez.
But just know that
Mais sachez juste que
working on your look,
travailler sur son look,
that matters too
ça a aussi une importance
when you're negotiating,
en négociation
because you're selling
parce que vous vendez
with your appearance.
avec votre apparence.
I'm telling you,
Je vous le dis,
it's up to you
juste vous en faites
to do what you want with it.
ce que vous voulez.
I'm just here to tell you
Moi, je suis là pour vous dire
what I really think,
ce que j'ai au fond
to give you the best advice.
pour vous délivrer le meilleur.
After that, it's your choice,
Après, c'est vous qui choisissez,
right?
on est d'accord ?
You're not judging me.
Vous ne me jugez pas.
You're judging me.
Vous me jugez.
I'm judging you too.
Je vous juge aussi.
We all judge each other.
On se juge tous.
But let's not judge.
Mais on ne juge pas.
Ok, fine.
Ok, fine.
Alright, no judging.
Ok, on ne se juge pas.
But still.
Mais bon.
So, in the end,
Donc, à la fin,
Everything adds up.
il y a tout qui s'ajoute.
It's not just the alcohol,
Ce n'est pas que l'alcool,
or the smell of cigarettes.
que l'odeur des cigarettes.
Personally, I have a hard time
Moi, j'ai du mal
shaking hands
à me serrer des mains
with people who smoke.
à des gens qui fument.
Sorry, that's just me.
Je suis désolé.
I'm just being honest.
Je vous le dis.
I honestly don't care.
J'en ai rien à foutre.
That's just how it is.
C'est comme ça.
What did you want
Qu'est-ce que je voulais
me to say about it?
que je vous le dise ?
So, I'm saying that at the end
Donc, je dis qu'à la fin
of the day,
de la journée,
it all adds up,
tout s'ajoute
and it's all about probabilities
et c'est des probabilités
that you stack up or not
que vous mettez ou pas
on your side every time.
de votre côté à chaque fois.
By the way,
By the way,
whether you like me
que vous m'aimez
or you don't like me,
ou que vous ne m'aimez pas,
it won't change anything in my life.
ça ne changera rien à ma life.
Because for me,
Parce que moi,
I'm not here to tell you
je ne veux pas vous dire
what you want to hear.
ce que vous avez envie d'entendre.
I want to tell you
Je veux vous dire
what I think
ce que je pense
will actually help you
qui va vous aider
to get better.
pour vous améliorer.
Whether you like it or not.
Que vous aimez ou pas.
Are we good with that or not?
On est d'accord avec ça ou pas ?
Okay, cool.
Ok, cool.
Does that work for you
Ça vous convient
or do you want me to switch up my style?
ou vous voulez que je change de style ?
Alright, perfect.
Ok, très bien.
I can be super boring too.
Je peux être super boring aussi.
So, qualification.
Alors, la qualification.
The buyer profile.
Le modèle acheteur.
Maud, I need you to find me
Maud, il faut que tu me trouves
some extra info back there.
du gras derrière là.
So, this is...
Donc, ça, c'est...
Take a picture of this.
Vous prenez en photo.
This is what I send
Ça, c'est ce que j'envoie
to qualify people
pour qualifier les gens
when I get an offer
quand j'ai une offre
or when someone
ou j'ai quelqu'un
wants to buy my house.
qui veut m'acheter ma maison.
I always ask
Je demande systématiquement
What's the nationality
C'est quoi la nationalité
about the buyer?
de l'acheteur ?
I'm sizing them up right now.
Je suis en train de le juger.
You know why?
Vous savez pourquoi ?
Because actually,
Parce qu'en fait,
it gives you clues.
ça vous donne des indications.
Well, okay, me, later on,
Déjà, bon, moi, après,
I'm in a...
je suis dans un...
I'm in Dubai.
Je suis à Dubaï.
Most people
Je suis dans un...
maybe here.
peut-être ici.
But tomorrow,
Mais demain,
when you have a buyer
quand vous avez un acheteur
who's buying a house from you
qui vous achète une maison
on the Croisette,
sur la croisette
and, I don't know,
et que, je ne sais pas moi,
it's a Saudi,
c'est un Saoudien,
well, that tells you something.
bon, ça vous donne une indication.
Are we on the same page or not?
On est d'accord ou pas ?
Alright, that's it.
Bon, voilà.
When tomorrow, someone...
Quand demain, quelqu'un...
Anyway,
Bon, bref,
I don't have time.
je n'ai pas le temps.
So, anyway.
Voilà, bref.
Number...
Nombre...
What's up?
Qu'est-ce qu'il y a ?
I'm moving forward.
J'avance.
Go ahead, I'm moving forward.
Avance, j'avance.
OK.
OK.
Minimum number of bedrooms.
Nombre de chambre minimum.
Ideal or latest moving date.
Idéal ou maximum moving date.
Maximum and ideal budget.
Maximal et idéal budget.
Which rentals
Quelles sont les locations
have they already looked at?
qu'ils ont déjà regardées ?
What type of buyer is it?
Quel est le type d'acheteur ?
Are they full cash
Il est full cash
or using the bank?
ou il va utiliser la banque ?
They're full cash.
Il est full cash.
That's my judgment.
Je l'ai jugé.
They're loaded.
Il est blindé.
Additional information.
Additionnale information.
Is there anything
Est-ce qu'il y a des choses
that's important?
qui sont importantes ?
Here, I can't afford
Ça, je n'ai pas le temps
to go too fast,
d'aller trop vite,
but it's super, super, super important
mais c'est très très très important
that you take this into account.
que vous preniez en considération ça.
Let me explain.
Je vous explique.
She's really quick.
Elle est très rapide.
I have to do it.
Je suis obligé de la faire.
It's a must.
C'est obligé.
It's there.
Elle est là.
There you go.
Voilà.
Alright.
Bon.
The guy, he's there.
Le gars, il est là.
He tells you,
Il vous dit
"No, but me,
« Non, mais moi,
I'm only looking for 4 bedrooms,
je ne cherche que 4 chambres
and my budget is 2 million.
et j'ai 2 millions de budget.
So, we agree
Donc, on est d'accord
that if I find
que si je trouve
the house of your dreams
la maison de tes rêves
with 3 bedrooms
à 3 chambres
for 2 million,
pour 2 millions,
you'll buy it.
tu achètes.
Yes, I'll buy it.
Oui, j'achète.
OK, it's not 4,
OK, ce n'est pas 4,
it's 3.
c'est 3.
And I do this
Et ça, je le fais
in these 3 categories.
dans ces 3 catégories.
So, we agree
Donc, on est d'accord
that if I find you
que si je te trouve
the house of your life
la maison de ta life
no, I won't buy
non, je n'achète pas
at 2 million for 3
à 2 millions de 3
because honestly,
parce que vraiment,
I just can't
je ne peux pas
because of the mortgage,
parce que mortgage,
and all that stuff.
machin et tout.
But on the other hand,
Par contre,
with 2, I can make it work.
de 2, je peux y arriver.
OK, so it's not 2,
OK, donc ce n'est pas 2,
it's from 2.
c'est de 2.
Location, same thing.
La localisation, pareil.
Me, I only want to be
Moi, je ne veux que être
in the south, in Nice.
dans le sud, à Nice.
OK, so I find
OK, donc je trouve
your dream house
la maison de tes rêves
in Cannes.
à Cannes.
You don't buy it.
Tu l'achètes pas.
Wait, maybe that's not
Attends, ça ne marche
really working.
peut-être pas trop.
He wants to buy in Cannes.
Il veut acheter à Cannes.
I tell him,
Je lui dis
"So, if I find you
« Donc, si je te trouve
your dream house
la maison de tes rêves
in Nice,
à Nice,
you won't buy it.
tu ne l'achètes pas.
Is that right?
On est d'accord ?
No, I won't buy it
Non, je n'achète pas
because my wife,
parce que ma femme,
the commute, the traffic, all that.
le trajet, le trafic et tout.
But on the other hand,
Par contre,
are you buying in Cannes-sur-Mer?
tu achètes à Cannes-sur-Mer ?
Are you buying in Antibes?
Tu achètes à Antibes ?
Yeah, I'm buying in Antibes.
Oui, j'achète à Antibes.
OK, so it's not Cannes.
OK, donc ce n'est pas Cannes.
Are you following me or not?
Vous me suivez ou pas ?
That's what I call qualifying.
Ça, c'est de la qualification.
It's B, A,
C'est B, A,
the qualification,
la qualification,
you have to do it
il faut le faire
to get, once again,
pour avoir, encore une fois,
some data.
de la data.
I'm speeding up.
J'accélère.
Take a photo,
Prenez en photo,
let's keep going with the qualification.
on enchaîne la qualification.
This is my template
Ça, c'est mon template
that I use
que j'utilise
when I get an offer.
quand j'ai une offre.
So, you can translate
Donc, vous pouvez traduire
this into French.
ça en français.
I'm asking for an offer.
Je demande une offre.
So, what's the company?
Donc, quelle est la boîte ?
Alright, you get the idea,
Bon, vous avez compris,
It's easy,
c'est facile,
we just ask for it.
on demande ça.
Boom, done, next.
Hop, c'est bon, next.
Come on, let's go.
Allez, hop.
One, two, three.
Un, deux, trois.
Figure it out however you want,
Tu te démerdes comme tu veux,
right now, I can't do it.
là, je n'y arriverai pas.
I'm telling you,
Je te le dis,
I'll manage later,
tout à l'heure, j'y arriverai,
but right now, I can't.
là, je n'y arriverai pas.
Investor model.
Modèle investisseur.
So, this is important,
Alors, ça, c'est important,
it's still for investors.
c'est investisseur quand même.
Can I get some details?
Je peux avoir du gras ?
Figure it out yourself,
Démerde-toi,
go talk to the others,
va parler aux autres,
I need more info.
j'ai besoin de gras.
So, investor profit,
Donc, profit de l'investisseur,
what is it?
c'est quoi ?
Is it a real estate agent,
C'est un agent immobilier,
is it a professional?
c'est un professionnel ?
No.
Non.
How much do they want to invest?
Combien il souhaite investir ?
Me, I came up with
Moi, j'ai défini
four tiers of investment.
quatre tiers d'investissement.
I recommend
Je vous conseille
you do the same.
de faire la même chose.
I've got tier 1s,
J'ai les tirs 1,
those are the ones who can pull the trigger
c'est ceux qui peuvent dégainer
or bring me
ou m'apporter
over 100 million dollars.
plus de 100 millions de dollars.
That's a tier 1.
C'est un tir 1.
Tier 2 is between 10 and 100.
Tirs 2, c'est entre 10 et 100.
Tier 3 is between 1 and 10.
Tirs 3, c'est entre 1 et 10.
Tier 4 is under 1.
Tirs 4, c'est en dessous de 1.
Right now,
Aujourd'hui,
I'm building an organization
je crée une organisation
to manage less,
pour gérer moins,
let's say, the tier 2s
on dirait que les tirs 2
and the tier 3s.
et les tirs 3.
If you're tier 2,
Vous êtes tir 2,
you're moving into the team.
vous allez passer dans l'équipe.
So, this is just,
Donc, ça, c'est pour,
basically,
tout simplement,
a way to get organized.
s'organiser à gérer.
That's how
C'est comme ça
we qualify
qu'on qualifie
and manage
et qu'on gère
and for you, it gives
et vous, ça vous donne
an idea of the scale.
un ordre d'idée.
Same thing in your CRM.
Pareil pour dans votre CRM.
Whether you have a real CRM
Que vous ayez un vrai CRM
or just an Excel sheet,
ou un fichier Excel,
you can put
vous pouvez mettre
your investors
les investisseurs
into different categories.
dans quelle catégorie ils sont.
That way,
Comme ça,
when you make
quand vous passez
calls to people,
des coups de téléphone aux gens,
you have all your tiers,
vous avez tous vos tirs
and a tier 1,
et un tir 1,
for you,
pour vous,
could be someone
ça peut être quelqu'un
who's worth a million.
qui pèse un million.
And a tier 2,
Et un tir 2,
is someone who puts in between,
c'est quelqu'un qui met entre,
let's say,
on va dire,
500,000,
500 000,
starting from 500,000.
à partir de 500 000.
You see what I mean?
Vous voyez ce que je veux dire ?
You set your own rules,
Vous définissez vos règles,
so that
comme ça,
you know later
vous savez après
when you follow up with people.
quand vous relancez les gens.
When can they invest?
Quand est-ce qu'il peut investir ?
I've got three types.
J'ai trois types.
Within 30 days,
Dans les 30 jours,
from 1 to 6 months,
de 1 à 6 mois,
over 6 months.
plus de 6 mois.
Super easy.
Très facile.
Just like that,
Comme ça,
it also gives you
ça vous donne aussi
an idea of the timing.
l'idée du timing.
How long does it take?
Combien de temps ?
What's the ROI?
Quel est le ROI ?
He wants 20%?
Il veut du 20% ?
Yeah, but me,
Ouais, mais moi,
I want 60%.
je veux 60%.
Okay,
Ok,
but you're making 10%.
mais tu fais du 10%.
You need to chill out.
Tu vas te détendre.
Because people,
Parce que les gens,
they want everything.
ils veulent tout.
Me,
Moi,
I want 60% Heroi
je veux 60% d'Heroi
in 12 months.
en 12 mois.
Calm down.
Calme-toi.
How much did you make
T'as fait combien
last year?
l'année dernière ?
11%.
11%.
Ok.
Ok.
If I give you 15,
Si je te donne du 15,
are you happy with that?
t'es content ?
Yeah, I'm happy.
Oui, je suis content.
So the ROI,
Donc le ROI,
it's not 60,
c'est pas 60,
it's 15.
c'est 15.
Are you with me so far?
Vous êtes avec moi, là ?
That's what I call qualifying.
Ça, c'est de la qualification.
You need to work on that.
Il faut avancer là-dessus.
It's super, super, super important.
C'est très, très, très, très important.
What deals
Quelles sont les opérations
does he already have going on,
qu'il a déjà en cours,
what has he already done,
qu'il a déjà réalisées
to see if he's a beginner or not?
pour voir si c'est un débutant ou pas ?
Alright, moving on.
Bon, j'enchaîne, là.
To negotiate well,
Pour bien négocier,
you need to know how to navigate,
il faut savoir naviguer,
be really smooth.
être très facile.
The example with the 26 properties,
L'exemple des 26 propriétés,
I don't have time
j'ai pas le temps
to explain it to you now.
de vous l'expliquer.
You can check it out,
Vous le regarderez,
it's in the MDB dashboard.
il est dans le dashboard de MDB.
Alright?
Ok ?
It's in your dashboard,
Il est dans votre dashboard,
in the MDB conference,
dans la conférence MDB
that I did last year.
que j'ai fait l'année dernière.
I go into detail there.
Je vais dans le détail.
That's what I explained to you this morning.
C'est ce que je vous ai expliqué ce matin.
The 26 properties,
Les 26 propriétés,
he bought 10 of them,
il en a acheté 10,
we had 16 left,
on en avait 16,
we split the 16,
on a divisé les 16,
we bought 2, 14.
on en a acheté 2, 14.
Anyway, you'll get it
Bref, vous comprendrez ça
when you watch the video.
quand vous regarderez la vidéo.
We don't have time
On n'a pas le temps
to go through it all now.
de la mettre à travers.
Okay?
Ok ?
All good?
C'est bon ?
Cool.
Cool.
Always be prepared.
Toujours préparer.
Briefcase,
Mallette,
laptop,
ordi,
case,
casse,
notebook,
carnet,
pen,
stylo,
that's what I always have,
c'est tout ce que j'ai toujours,
that's me,
c'est moi,
all the time.
tout le temps.
You'll always see me
Vous allez toujours me voir
with my briefcase
avec ma mallette
that weighs a ton
qui pèse une tonne
because I always want
parce que je veux toujours
to be ready to pitch,
être préparé à pitcher,
to show things,
à montrer,
to sketch things out,
à dessiner,
to take notes,
à prendre des notes,
to visualize.
à visualiser.
Okay?
Ok ?
So,
Donc,
have you ever
est-ce que vous avez déjà
found yourself in a situation
retrouvé dans une situation
where you have just one investor,
où vous n'avez qu'un investisseur,
but you don't have your pitch deck,
vous n'avez pas votre pitch deck,
your presentation?
votre présentation ?
You might miss out on a chance
Vous ratez une opportunité
to really hook someone.
potentiellement de creuser quelqu'un.
So, pitching a partner,
Donc, pitcher un partenaire,
same thing.
pareil.
Always be prepared.
Toujours préparer.
Brian.
Brian.
Brian,
Brian,
try to close him if you can.
essayez de vouloir le closer potentiellement.
This is someone
C'est quelqu'un
I’m going to ask questions to
où je vais poser des questions
at the first meeting,
sur le premier rendez-vous,
like how much he wanted to make.
combien il voulait gagner.
Then I came back a second time
Je suis revenu la deuxième fois
for my informal meeting
dans mon rendez-vous informel
with an Excel file
avec un fichier Excel
and I told him
en lui disant
"Look,
« Voilà,
if you want to make
si tu veux gagner
a million dollars with us,
un million de dollars avec nous,
here’s what we need to do."
il faut qu'on fasse ça.
Two million dollars,
Deux millions de dollars,
then you need to do this.
il faut que tu en fasses ça.
Three million dollars,
Trois millions de dollars,
here’s what we have to do.
il faut qu'on fasse ça.
And I’ll show
Et je vais montrer
the different scenarios and everything.
les différents scénarios et tout.
What do you think
Qu'est-ce que vous pensez
he
que lui,
Brian, thinks
il en pense Brian
when I go see him
quand je vais le voir
for the second meeting
en deuxième rendez-vous
and I show up
et que j'arrive
with all these scenarios,
avec des scénarios,
With actions?
avec des actions ?
Do you think he's happy,
Vous pensez qu'il est content,
thinking to himself,
il se dit
"I'm serious,
« Je suis sérieux,
I'm not here to mess around, or what?
je ne suis pas là pour rigoler ou pas ?
Because we're not here
Parce qu'on n'est pas là
to make friends.
pour se faire des amis.
Even though,
Même si,
obviously,
bien évidemment,
you will make friends.
vous allez vous faire des amis.
But that's just a bonus.
Mais c'est un bonus.
Otherwise,
Sinon,
go somewhere else.
il faut aller dans d'autres endroits.
Nightclubs,
Boîte de nuit,
whatever, all that,
machin et tout,
do your thing.
faites vos trucs.
But if it's business,
Et si c'est business,
it's serious.
c'est sérieux.
Alright?
D'accord ?
Of course we build
Bien sûr qu'on développe
relationships, and so on.
des relations, etc.
But you get it, right?
Mais vous comprenez ?
So, get ready.
Donc, préparez-vous.
Do some due diligence
Faites une due diligence
on your contacts.
sur vos contacts
before the meeting
avant le rendez-vous
and after the meeting.
et après le rendez-vous.
Due diligence,
Due diligence,
so you analyze
donc vous analysez
what's going on.
ce qui se passe.
You get the idea.
Vous avez compris.
Alright, you don't really
Bon, vous n'avez pas
feel like explaining all that.
envie de vous expliquer ça.
So get organized.
Organisez alors.
A good negotiator,
Un bon négociateur,
is organized.
il est organisé.
Who here has ever confirmed
Qui a déjà confirmé
a meeting by phone
un rendez-vous par téléphone
and the person,
et la personne,
they don't show up
elle ne se pointe pas
because they forgot
parce qu'elle a oublié
about your meeting?
votre rendez-vous ?
It happens, right.
Ça rémakie ça.
OK,
OK,
let's send calendar
on envoie des invitations
invites
calendaires
by email.
avec des e-mails.
Right?
Hein ?
That's better, isn't it?
C'est mieux, non ?
Because now it's in their calendar.
Parce que c'est dans leur calendrier.
They have reminders and everything.
Ils ont des rappels et tout.
That's why it's set up like that.
C'est pour ça que c'est fait.
Get organized with this.
Organisez-vous là-dessus.
Why does this matter
Pourquoi ça joue
in your negotiation?
dans votre négociation ?
Because the timer
Parce que le timer,
shows you're serious.
ça montre que vous êtes sérieux.
I explained that to you earlier.
Je vous l'ai expliqué tout à l'heure.
Bam!
Bam !
Smile!
Smile !
It's contagious.
C'est contagieux.
Don't you feel like smiling?
On n'a pas envie de sourire ?
Everyone's smiling.
Tout le monde sourit.
Just remember,
Dites-vous bien
when you look grumpy,
que quand vous faites la gueule,
people will look grumpy back at you.
les gens vont vous faire la gueule.
We can try,
On peut essayer,
can we do a test?
on peut faire un test ?
Let's smile.
Sourions.
Wait,
Attendez,
we're not doing a test.
on ne fait pas un test.
I'm going up front.
Je passe en haut.
OK, we're good.
OK, c'est bon.
Go back to your normal posture.
Reprenez votre posture normale.
OK, you're smiling.
OK, vous souriez.
That's good.
Ça marche.
It's contagious.
C'est contagieux.
It's important.
C'est important.
People want to be
Les gens veulent être
around people
avec des gens
who have good energy.
qui ont une bonne énergie.
It works with women,
Ça marche avec les femmes,
it works with men,
ça marche avec les hommes,
it works with everyone.
ça marche avec tout le monde.
You can smile
On peut sourire
and be polite,
et être courtois,
feel good, comfortable,
bien, à l'aise,
relaxed, good vibes.
tranquille, bonne énergie.
Who wants to be
Qui veut être
around people like us?
avec des gens qui sont nous ?
How's it going?
Comment ça va ?
To feel better.
Pour aller mieux.
No.
Non.
I'm good,
Moi, ça va,
I'm at the top.
ça va à la top.
Always.
Toujours.
Always on top.
Toujours au top.
I'm good,
Ça va,
I'm at 1% on my hoop.
je suis à 1% sur ma hoop.
Everyone who has a hoop,
Tous ceux qui ont une hoop,
they know what it is.
ils savent ce que c'est.
I'm on top of my game.
Je suis au top.
No problem at all.
Zéro problème.
You can't know that.
Tu ne peux pas le savoir.
Always on top.
Toujours au top.
It's important
C'est important
what you give off.
ce que vous dégagez.
Be reasonable.
Être raisonnable.
Oh damn,
Oh putain,
what are we gonna do?
comment on va faire ?
So,
Donc,
be reasonable.
être raisonnable.
70% for the investor,
70% pour l'investisseur,
30% for us.
30% pour nous.
Just know there's a trick
Sachez qu'il y a un truc
in negotiations
en négociation
that works like crazy
qui marche de folie
that I'm giving you.
que je vous donne.
A little secret like that,
Un petit secret comme ça,
right now.
là, maintenant.
Poof.
Pouf.
When you make a deal,
Quand vous faites un deal,
always suggest
proposez toujours
a return on investment
un retour sur investissement
The investor gets priority.
prioritaire à l'investisseur.
It could be 10%,
Ça peut être 10%,
it could be 12%,
ça peut être 12%,
it could be 15%.
ça peut être 15%.
If they put in the money,
Si jamais il met l'argent
or the people
ou les gens
who put in the money,
qui mettent l'argent,
including you, by the way,
y compris vous-même d'ailleurs,
if the project falls through,
si jamais le projet tombe,
the first X%
les premiers X%
goes to the investor.
vont à l'investisseur.
Fair.
Fair.
Makes sense.
Normal.
That costs you nothing
Ça, ça coûte zéro
when everything goes well.
quand tout se passe bien.
But you put it
Mais vous l'avez mis
in your terms and conditions,
dans vos termes et vos conditions,
that's what makes them want
c'est ce qui veut faire
to do the deal with you
le deal avec vous
and not with someone else.
et pas avec quelqu'un d'autre.
Are you with me?
Vous me suivez ?
So us,
Donc nous,
we've done 30 exits,
on a fait 30 exits,
31,
31,
I won't even go into the rest,
je ne passe même pas le reste,
I'm actually talking about Dubai,
je parle justement à Dubaï,
we guarantee the cost of the work.
on garantit le coût des travaux.
Meaning, if it costs us,
C'est-à-dire que si ça nous coûte,
we tell you it costs
on te dit que ça coûte
one million dollars,
un million de dollars,
but it ends up costing us one million one hundred,
ça nous coûte un million cent,
we're the ones who cover
c'est nous qui prenons
the extra hundred thousand.
les cent mille à charge.
You can do
Vous pouvez faire
something similar.
la même chose similaire.
I'm just giving you some ideas.
Je vous donne des idées.
So the hurdle rate,
Donc le hurdle rate,
that's it,
c'est ça,
it's that famous preferred return,
c'est le fameux retour prioritaire
and having exit alternatives.
et avoir des alternatives d'exit.
If we can't
On n'arrive pas
resell the house,
à revendre la maison,
we can rent it out.
on peut la louer.
One of the partners,
Un des partenaires,
he just rented out his house
il vient de louer sa maison
for one million dollars a year,
un million de dollars à l'année,
paid up front,
payé up front,
billionaire.
milliardaire.
We take that, right?
On les prend, non ?
We keep the house
On garde la maison
if we can't sell.
si on n'arrive pas à vendre.
Who wouldn't want
Qui n'a pas envie
to pocket a million dollars
de prendre un million de dollars
just like that, up front,
comme ça à up front
for two months?
pendant deux mois ?
This is just to give you
C'est juste pour vous donner
an example.
un exemple.
So tomorrow,
Donc demain,
the project,
le projet,
doesn't go through.
il ne se fait pas.
You end up
Vous vous retrouvez
with the project
avec le projet
because there's a war,
parce qu'il y a la guerre,
just like that,
tiens,
out of nowhere.
comme par hasard.
And you can't
Et vous n'arrivez pas
sell
à vendre
for whatever reason.
pour x ou x raison.
Just so you know,
Pour info,
that's not our situation.
ce n'est pas notre cas.
We're actually negotiating
On est en train de négocier
and making deals,
de faire des deals,
but that's a whole other topic.
mais c'est un autre débat là.
Okay?
Ok ?
Me, I just wanted
Moi, j'avais envie
to go off on a tangent here.
de digresser là.
So, what I'm saying is,
Donc, ce que je veux dire,
you can totally
c'est que vous pouvez très bien
rent out the properties,
louer les biens,
hold onto the asset,
garder l'actif
and then sell later.
et puis revendre plus tard.
No problem.
Pas un problème.
So, reassure people,
Donc, rassurez les gens,
be reasonable.
soyez raisonnables.
Part 3.
Partie 3.
My tips.
Mes tips.
Come on, picture.
Allez, photo.
Boom.
Bam.
The info,
L'information,
we already talked about it.
on en a parlé.
All good?
C'est bon ?
Click here.
Cliquez là.
One click.
Un clic.
Two clicks.
Deux clics.
See,
Tu vois,
it's your fault.
c'est ta faute.
It's Maud's fault.
C'est la faute de Maud.
You can tell her.
Vous lui direz.
I'm in front,
Je suis devant,
you can't see?
on ne voit pas ?
Alright.
D'accord.
Is that better now?
C'est mieux là ?
Okay.
Ok.
Information.
Information.
Listening data.
Data sur l'écoute.
I'll make this super quick.
Je le fais très rapide.
Like I was saying,
Comme je vous le disais,
people interrupt
les gens interrompent
every 17 seconds.
toutes les 17 secondes.
People remember only 25% to 50%,
25% à 50%,
that's what actually sticks.
c'est ce que les gens retiennent.
Go read up on it if you want.
Vous irez lire les trucs.
The 10% rule.
Le principe du 10%.
Try to put at least 10%
Essayez de mettre au moins 10%
on the table right from the start.
sur la table dès le début.
Show that it works.
Montrez que ça marche.
I'm looking for 100,000.
Je cherche 100 000.
I've already put in 30,000,
J'ai déjà mis 30 000,
so I just need 70,000 more.
il me manque 70 000.
That's not the same thing
Ce n'est pas la même chose
as going to someone
que d'aller voir quelqu'un
and asking for 100,000.
et lui demander 100 000.
Bring proof,
Apporter des preuves,
build trust.
créer la confiance.
Alright, let's press here.
Bon là, on appuie là.
Break down your actions.
Séquencez vos actions.
That's super important.
Ça, c'est très important.
Sorry, but it really is important.
Je suis désolé, c'est important.
So, first,
Donc, d'abord,
you've got seven steps
vous avez sept étapes
before you even talk to an investor.
avant d'aller parler à un investisseur.
First one is you.
La première, c'est vous déjà.
Would you sign yourself?
Est-ce que vous, vous signerez ?
Does the project
Est-ce que le projet
make at least 30% HeroE
fait au moins 30% d'HeroE
over 12 months?
sur 12 mois ?
If not, don't do it.
Sinon, n'y allez pas.
It's not profitable enough.
Ce n'est pas assez rentable.
These are tips.
C'est des tips.
You need to find profitable deals.
Il faut trouver des projets rentables.
A bankable project.
Projet bankable.
Bankable.
Bankable.
Is the project worth it?
Est-ce que le projet vaut le coup ?
The project is worth it.
Le projet vaut le coup.
Is the area doing well?
Est-ce que le secteur marche ?
Yes.
Oui.
Move if you have to.
Déménager s'il le faut.
That's it.
Voilà.
That's life.
C'est la vie.
What's the best way
Quel est le meilleur moyen
to get started
de démarrer
for all beginners?
pour tous les débutants ?
She erased
Elle a effacé
and it said
et il y a marqué
primary residence.
résidence principale.
She wrote
Elle a mis
live with your parents.
vivez chez vos parents.
It was more like
C'était plutôt
primary residence,
résidence principale,
do some renovations,
faites des travaux,
while you're renovating,
pendant les travaux,
go live with your parents
allez vivre chez vos parents
and your friends.
et vos amis.
What's the problem?
C'est quoi le problème ?
For 3 months,
Pendant 3 mois,
4 months,
4 mois,
5 months,
5 mois,
6 months
6 mois
to go cash in
pour aller encaisser
a big check.
un gros chèque.
Why not?
Why not ?
I put a smiley for you.
Pourquoi pas ?
Then, you,
Ensuite, vous,
your finances,
vos finances,
how much are you able
combien vous êtes capable
to put in?
de mettre ?
Next,
Ensuite,
we go see the bank
on va voir la banque
and we say,
et en disant
I've got this project,
j'ai ce projet-là,
if I bring 30%,
si j'apporte les 30%,
will you finance the other 70%?
tu me finances les 70%,
Yes,
oui,
here you go,
tiens,
here's a part of it,
voilà une partie,
etc.
etc.
Okay,
Ok,
you come back with the agreement
vous venez avec l'accord
and then,
et ensuite,
you talk to your investors.
vous parlez à vos investisseurs.
So,
Donc,
the project,
le projet,
it's awesome,
il démonte,
you explain everything.
vous expliquez tout.
Me,
Moi,
I'll put in 10,000,
je mets 10 000,
50,000,
50 000,
100,000,
100 000,
we already have 100,000,
on a déjà 100 000,
the bank is backing us,
la banque nous suit,
we only have 200,000 left
il ne nous reste que 200 000
out of a million,
sur un million,
for example.
par exemple.
That's not the same project.
Ce n'est pas le même projet.
We agree
On est d'accord
it's not the same project
que ce n'est pas le même projet
as if you asked
que si vous demandez
for all the money right away
tout de suite l'argent
from the investor?
à l'investisseur ?
Okay.
Ok.
Alright,
Bon,
listen up,
écoutez,
personal audits,
audits de perso,
write it down,
notez-le,
you'll read it,
vous lirez,
you'll do it at home.
vous le ferez à la maison.
There you go,
Voilà,
let's go,
hop là,
part 4!
partie 4 !
Alright,
Hop là,
take a picture.
prenez en photo.
Who deserves to win the most?
Qui mérite le plus de gagner ?
In a real estate SPV,
Dans un dédié immobilier,
that's interesting.
c'est intéressant ça.
Alright,
Allez,
the one who raises the funds,
celui qui lève les fonds,
but doesn't bring any cash.
mais pas de cash.
So,
Donc,
between 30 and 40%,
entre 30 et 40%,
the dealmaker,
le dealmaker,
between 25 and 35%,
entre 25 et 35%,
execution,
l'exécution,
between 15 and 25,
entre 15 et 25,
sales gets between 10 and 20.
le sales entre 10 et 20.
It depends,
Ça dépend,
obviously,
bien évidemment,
but this is just to give you
mais c'est juste pour vous donner
a rough idea.
un ordre d'idée.
It depends on the deal.
Ça dépend du deal.
If the deal,
Le deal,
is hard to finance?
il est dur à financer ?
Finance,
La finance,
is number one,
c'est le numéro 1,
so they'll get the biggest share.
donc il va y gagner plus.
If the opportunity,
L'opportunité,
is off-market.
elle est off-market.
The guy who finds the deal,
Le mec qui trouve le deal,
will get more.
il va avoir plus.
The project,
Le projet,
it's complicated.
il est complexe.
Are the renovations heavy?
Les travaux sont lourds ?
That's the execution guy.
C'est le mec de l'exécution.
The market,
Le marché,
is it tough?
il est dur ?
That's the sales part.
C'est la vente.
OK,
OK,
next.
next.
Part 5,
Partie 5,
we're moving fast now.
ça va vite là.
It's good,
Ça va,
it's going quickly.
ça va vite.
OK,
OK,
saving the best for last.
le meilleur pour la fin.
Presentation,
Présentation,
no, wait,
non là,
I'm going to give you a practical tip.
je vais vous donner un tip pratique.
When I present to someone,
Quand je présente à quelqu'un,
I always have three things open.
j'ai toujours trois choses ouvertes.
I have my Green Bull Group presentation,
J'ai ma présentation Green Bull Group,
where I introduce the group,
où je présente le groupe,
super quick.
très rapide.
Just know that's it,
Dites-vous que c'est ça,
I do it in 5 minutes.
je le fais en 5 minutes.
Then,
Ensuite,
Green Bull Properties,
Green Bull Properties,
I explain it in 10-15 minutes.
j'explique en 10-15 minutes.
And then,
Et ensuite,
I've got the track record file
j'ai le fichier du track record
with all the green lines,
avec toutes les lignes vertes,
where you can see those are sales,
où il voit que c'est des ventes,
with the returns on investment.
avec les retours sur investissement.
That,
Ça,
that's my desktop,
c'est mon desktop,
just to show you
juste pour vous montrer
when I explain to someone
quand j'explique à quelqu'un
what I've got.
ce que j'ai.
And this,
Et ça,
this is my business plan.
c'est mon business plan.
Take a picture of this,
Prenez ça en photo,
we're done,
on a fini,
can you believe it?
t'imagines ?
Almost.
Bientôt.
So,
Donc,
this,
ça,
this is the business plan.
c'est le business plan.
So,
Donc,
this,
ça,
this is all the...
c'est toutes les...
Since I'm almost done,
Vu que j'ai bientôt fini,
Maude,
Maude,
Can I have 3 minutes?
je peux prendre 3 minutes ?
3 minutes,
3 minutes,
I don't know.
je sais pas.
No?
Non ?
How much will you give me?
Comment tu me donnes ?
2 minutes?
2 minutes ?
1 minute?
1 minute ?
Come on,
Allez,
I don't care,
je m'en fous,
I'm not moving.
je bouge pas.
Come,
Viens,
come on.
viens.
So,
Donc,
2 minutes.
2 minutes.
2 minutes,
2 minutes,
thanks.
merci.
So,
Donc,
this,
ça,
is very,
c'est très,
very,
très,
very important.
très important.
This,
Ça,
is if tomorrow,
c'est si demain,
you ask us for money,
vous nous demandez de l'argent à nous,
This is a table I'm going to ask you to fill out.
c'est un tableau que je vais vous demander de remplir.
It's all this information.
C'est toutes ces informations.
Without this info,
Sans ces informations,
there's no answer.
il n'y a pas de réponse.
So,
Donc,
let's go through them one by one.
on va les voir un par un.
The project,
Le projet,
the opportunity.
l'opportunité.
First,
Déjà,
the location,
l'endroit,
where is it?
c'est où ?
Because that,
Parce que ça,
that tells us right away,
ça va nous indiquer tout de suite,
if we go for it or not.
on y va ou on n'y va pas.
Straight up,
Direct,
the location.
l'endroit.
what kind is it?
c'est quoi comme type ?
Is it land,
C'est un terrain,
who are the partners,
c'est qui les partenaires,
who's the developer?
c'est qui le développeur ?
the analysis date.
la date d'analyse.
So,
Donc,
that's the date we get the property.
c'est la date à laquelle on reçoit le bien.
Next,
Ensuite,
the income.
les revenus.
There are always,
Il y a toujours,
in the income,
dans les revenus,
in the costs,
dans les coûts,
in the profits,
dans les profits,
there are always three scenarios.
il y a toujours trois scénarios.
Me,
Moi,
I always want to see three scenarios.
je veux voir toujours trois scénarios.
I want the minimum,
Je veux le minimum,
the worst-case scenario.
le pire des cas.
I want the base,
Je veux le base
and I want the maximum scenario.
et je veux le scénario maximum.
Because actually,
Parce qu'en fait,
depending on who you're talking to,
en fonction des gens à qui vous allez parler,
you'll have people who are super hyped,
vous allez avoir des gens qui sont très chauds patates
who will look at the maximum,
qui vont regarder le maximum
then the base,
et ensuite le base
and then the worst.
et ensuite le worst.
You have the analytics,
Vous avez les analytiques,
the data-driven types,
data-driven,
whatever,
machin,
who are there,
qui sont là,
whoa,
oula,
this looks complicated and all,
ça a l'air compliqué et tout,
whatever,
machin,
what's the worst-case scenario?
c'est quoi le pire des cas ?
They'll start with the worst-case scenario.
Ils vont commencer avec le pire des cas.
Then,
Ensuite,
the base case,
le base,
they won't even look at the target.
ils ne regarderont même pas le target.
Same goes for costs,
Pareil pour les coûts,
same for profits.
pareil pour les profits.
So,
Donc,
that,
ça,
that's nine key figures.
c'est neuf chiffres clés.
Next,
Ensuite,
funds and structures.
fonds et structures.
So,
Donc,
how much are you looking for?
quel est le montant que vous recherchez ?
I'm looking for 3 million.
Je recherche 3 millions.
What are you offering for 3 million?
Qu'est-ce que vous proposez pour 3 millions ?
Well,
Eh bien,
70% of the profit shares.
70% des participations sur les profits.
How much are you taking as a management fee?
Combien tu prends de management fee ?
So,
Donc,
how much are you charging?
combien tu charges ?
I'm going to take 1%,
Je vais prendre 1%,
2%,
2%,
whatever,
peu importe,
on the deal.
sur l'opération.
What's your skin in the game?
Quel est ton skin in the game ?
How much capital has already been invested
Quel est le capital qui a déjà été investi
by the project leaders
par les porteurs de projets
or investors in the project?
ou les investisseurs dans le projet ?
How much is it?
C'est combien ?
Well,
Eh bien,
we've already put in 500,000.
on a déjà mis 500 000.
Okay,
Ok,
that's good,
c'est bien,
you're in.
tu es in.
How much more are you planning to add?
Combien tu as prévu de rajouter ?
Well,
Eh bien,
we,
nous,
we're planning to add 100,000.
on a prévu de rajouter 100 000.
Okay,
Ok,
so that makes 600.
ça fait 600.
That means there's only 400 left, for example.
Il ne reste que 400 par exemple.
So,
Donc,
this,
ça,
this is important,
c'est important,
it shows the skin in the game.
ça montre le skin in the game.
The timeline,
La timeline,
what's your date for raising the funds?
quelle est ta date pour lever les fonds ?
Your deadline?
Ta deadline ?
Okay,
Ok,
that's good,
c'est bon,
I'm done.
j'ai fini.
What's your deadline
Quelle est ta deadline
for the project duration?
la durée du projet ?
And I want you to score
Et je te demande de scorer
the opportunity from 1 to 10.
entre 1 et 10 l'opportunité.
Why would you rate it between 3 and 6?
Pourquoi investir entre 3 à 6 points ?
Explain it clearly.
Bien expliqué.
And what are the main risks?
Et les principaux risques ?
Simple,
Simple,
clear,
net,
efficient.
efficace.
Yes or no?
Oui ou non ?
That's how you'll pitch to people.
C'est comme ça que vous allez picher les gens.
Did you get value today?
Vous avez eu de la valeur aujourd'hui ?
Okay,
Ok,
thanks, because they're kicking me out.
merci parce qu'on me dégage.
Alright,
Allez,
thanks.
merci.
Come on,
faites de l'argent !
Change your life a little!
Changez de vie un peu là !
Here you go.
Tiens.
ячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячяч
ячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячячяч